<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "./tX.dtd">
<section name="changelog">
 <changelog>
  <version name="3.82" unreleased="true">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
	 in order to have a SPAM protected online version of the ChangeLog this 
	 document is now generated from XML sources.
	 </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     merged a patch from <person>
      <name>Martin Habets</name>
      <email>errandir_news@mph.eclipse.co.uk</email>
     </person> that fixes big endian audio playback with ALSA.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     applied a fix from <person>
      <name>Juha Erkkila</name>
      <email>erkkila@cc.jyu.fi</email>
     </person> that makes tX work on systems that don't have procfs mounted.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added an optional Dry/Wet control for all LADSPA plugins. Simply click on
     the plugin's label to add or remove the additional control.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added an additional stereo effects queue that allows loading stereo LADPSA
     plugins. The stereo effects are located below the mono effects - to add a
     new instance press the "Stereo FX" button and select the plugin of your
     choice.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed the plugin menu - empty categories no longer get a menu entry</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     plugins that do not qualify as realtime capable will now be disabled.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     I'm fed up with terminatorX related security postings, so the old suid-root
     method had to go. To achieve realtime scheduling you now have three
     options:<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        a) run terminatorX as root (obviously dangerous and not recommended)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        b) build terminatorX with capabilities enabled and install it suid-root.
        Due to the use of PR_SET_KEEPCAPS this will work on Linux _only_</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        c) use the JACK backend with "POSIX draft capabilities" (see jackd
        manpage)</para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Loading sets with missing LADPSA plugins no longer crash tX.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed a bug that made reading error messages impossible with the load
     dialog open.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The engine now handles audiodevices that break down when already in
     playback mode more gracefully. This really necessary when jack decides to
     kick us out.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     All vu meters are stereo now. Having a mono widget for a stereo thing just
     didn't make any sense anymore.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     modified the render loop to comply with LADSPA V1.1: 0 db is now at 1.0f.
     This makes a lot of plugins work with terminatorX that haven't worked with
     previous releases.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     data send to the JACK backend no goes through the "Anti-Clip-Device", too.
     Unless you #define TX_DO_CLIP of course.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     I've drawn some new icons with the cool 
	 <link ref="http://www.inkscape.org">inkscape</link>.
	 They're now being built into terminatorX as gdk-pixbuf c-source code, so they
     actually do alpha blending.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Wrote support for gtk+'s new FileChooser widget - will be enabled
     automatically when configure finds a gtk+ >= 2.4.0</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed the buffer overflows detected by <person>
      <name>c0wboy</name>
      <email>c0wboy@tiscali.it</email>
     </person> in his outsiders-terminatorX-001.txt advisory.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Support for gtk+ startup notification.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     "README.GNOME" was outdated so it had to go.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     merged parts of a patch graciously contributed by <person>
      <name>Adam King</name>
      <email>aking@lgh.com.au</email>
     </person><itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        Simpler min/maximization for the control panels</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        Bugfix for sequencer menu crash</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        The panel formally known as "Trigger" is now known as "Playback"></para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added cpu-overload detection - currently disabled</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.81">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     JACK doesn't seem to like SCHED_FIFO clients so I added a little test that
     will set SCHED_OTHER when jack output was selected. This will work for true
     root or a capabilities-enabled suid-root binary only.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     removed the disfunctional "Cancel" button from the load-progress dialog.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     switched default MIDI mapping to non-destructive. (previous settings will
     not be overwritten now).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added a default MIDI mapping accessible via the "Turntables" menu. The
     actual mapping is documented in the manual.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed a bug that caused enabling sync-client setting via MIDI to fail.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     when compiled with rt-scheduling suppport terminatorX will now display the
     resulting scheduling policy in the "About" dialog.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     if terminatorX was setup to use realtime priority for the audio engine
     thread but you dont want it - disable realtime scheduling in the
     Preferences dialog. This works with capabilities _ONLY_.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     if you don't want to confirm program termination every time you can now
     disable "Ask for Quit confirmation" in the Preferences.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added support for Linux' POSIX capabilities. This allows a suid-root
     installed terminatorX binary to drop root privileges much earlier than with
     the old approach (so it should be more secure). Requires the libcap
     library.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     obligatory documentation updates - clicking on the sub-sections should now
     work.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     removed gtk+ 1.2 cruft - terminatorX now compiles with gtk+ 2.2 and
     *_DISABLE_DEPRECATED macros enabled. To verfiy that you can run configure
     with --disable-deprecated.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     terminatorX now has a JACK backend. Currently it works like this: on
     startup tX will connect to the JACK daemon - if the daemon is not available
     on startup JACK output is not available. When the audio engine is turned
     off, tX emits silence via the JACK ports, so you can leave the ports
     connected.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     sick of green - you can now configure the colors terminatorX should use for
     the audio display as well as the vu meters in the Preferences dialog.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     hopefully fixed wrong setting of the master volume when loading set files.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     some ALSA installations seem to core on snd_pcm_hw_params_free() after
     sound device init. So freeing the hw_params can now be explicitly disabled
     in the Preferences - if terminatorX crashes right after hitting the "Power
     On" button it might be necessary to activate this for your ALSA setup. This
     probably results in a tiny memory leak - but on leak vs core you might
     decide for leak. Note: I even enabled the leak by default now.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed a bug that caused turntable 1 to get the focus on entering Mouse Grab
     mode even when it's audio panel was minimized.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     MIDI mappings can now have "bounds", meaning that the incoming MIDI signals
     can modify the parameter within the given range only.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     introduced a new way of assigning MIDI controllers to parameters: simply
     right-click on a parameter's control: a menu with "MIDI Learn" and "Remove
     MIDI Binding" will pop up - select "MIDI Learn" and send the corresponding
     MIDI event.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed a bug in the MIDI callback thanks to <person>
      <name>David Hamilton</name>
      <email>daham2@student.monash.edu</email>
     </person></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     running suid root (the old way) was reported exploitable by <person>
      <name>Andrew Griffiths</name>
      <email>andrewg@felinemenace.org</email>
     </person> - the described environment variable based exploit was fixed - however there are
     possibly other ways to exploit it. So the old method of running suid root
     has been disabled by default. On Linux systems you really should use the
     capabilities based approach (see above). If really want to use the old
     suid-root solution run configure with --enable-suidroot.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     often, you record events and mess things up - in this case I'd often prefer
     dropping the complete take instead of recording a bad perfomance - which is
     why you now can activate "Confirm Recorded Events" from the "Sequencer"
     menu. When enabled terminatorX will ask whether to actually record or drop
     the events created for the last take. The setting for this flag is stored
     in your ~/.terminatorXrc.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     introduced a new "Sequencer" menu that allows to delete events of a
     specific type (all, all for certain turntable, all for a certain parameter)
     from the sequencer. Events can be deleted for the complete song, upto the
     current song position or from the current song position. Yeah, I know,
     termintorX is lacking a proper event-editor here, so where's your patch? ;)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     switching the X11 mouse cursor when the user has to wait for terminatorX to
     finish some operation</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed a sequencer bug: the events for master pitch and volume weren't
     erased correctly when another set was loaded</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed FreeBSD issues with the configure script</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed compilation issues for gcc 2.95.x</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.80">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     I've invested quite some time in valgrinding this release, among other
     things a major mem leak showed up - the sample memory wasn't being free'd
     correctly which is now corrected along with many other things. valgrind is
     a very helpful tool indeed.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Added a new Pitch Calculator that allows adjusting a turntable's pitch to
     that of the master turntable. This makes synchronizing finely cut loop
     samples really easy</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     XML based set files can get rather huge when they contain a lot of
     sequencer events - to solve this terminatorX now uses zlib to save
     compressed set files if enabled in the preferences dialog.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     I hacked support for Steve Harris' cool liblrdf - if you've got that
     library setup correctly and you use Steve's wonderful plugin collection
     with RDF description you should get a nicely structured menu when clicking
     on the "FX" button. All plugins not categorized through RDF files go to the
     "Unclassified" category.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     I'm no longer including the html and ps versions of the manual - it's now
     attached in it's XML/DocBook source and will be installed via scrollkeeper.
     terminatorX offers a menu entry to start gnome-help to display the manual.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Reworked the Preferences dialog - I now use glade-2 to create that code -
     I'm fed up with copy'n'pasting gtk+ code so now I'll let glade-2 do this
     whereever possible. The glade project files are included with this tarball
     in case you want to mess with them.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Switched to a fixed blocksize (1 ms) for rendering. This finally allows to
     playback set files with events recorded on machines with small buffer sizes
     on slow machines with large buffer sizes. The buffersize of the audiodevice
     has no effect on the "operating" blocksize anymore. Note that the samlping
     rate has a - very small - effect though. Depending on the sampling rate
     terminatorX will try to find a blocksize that fits exactly 1 ms - while
     this is easy for "straight" sampling rates (22000 32000 48000) this results
     in "44.1" samples for 44100 Hz.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Finally hacked a native ALSA backend. It's in "Works For Me" TM state.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Added "Remove Binding" button</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     MIDI now uses a GIOCallback so the effect of MIDI controllers is visible
     even without the audio engine turned on.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Reworked the mastergui for better usabilty and less space consumption, yes,
     terminatorX now features a boring menubar - which helps using it on small
     displays quite a bit, and should be easier to handle for first-time users.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Implemented a suggestion from <person>
      <name>Darrick Servis</name>
      <email>darrick@dcn.davis.ca.us</email>
     </person> that stops clipping in the mixer routine. The outgoing signal is now limited as
     it should be, which improves the output quality for signals too loud
     significantly.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     MIDI mappings are now stored within the (new) tX set files.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Applied a patch from <person>
      <name>Arthur Peters</name>
      <email>amp@singingwizard.org</email>
     </person> which brings preliminary MIDI support to terminatorX. This is realized via the
     ALSA sequencer interface, so in order for it to compile you have to have
     the ALSA devel packages installed. ./configure will autodetect them.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed a bug in XML serialization that dropped strings' contents.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     You can now hit "F11" to turn fullscreen mode on/off - this will help using
     terminatorX on small DJ laptops. Note that the key will have no effect in
     scratch mode - hit it before you enter grab mode. This feature requires a
     NETWM compliant window manager.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     terminatorX now stores set files as XML documents, too - so terminatorX has
     become terminatorXML finally. Note: for sets with a large number of events
     recorded into the sequencer - the XML based set files can grow significally
     larger than the old ones (see "compression" above)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The old code to support the obsolete binary tX file formats has now been
     scheduled for deletion. It's been moved into the tX_legacy* source files
     and it will be built only when "--enable-legacy" was used on configuring
     terminatorX (which is the default). Expect this to become disabled and then
     totally removed from the sources in future.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Enhanced audio data display - you can now zoom into the audio signal, which
     should allow much more precise scratching with larger audio files (ie
     complete tracks). On playback terminatorX will scroll the displayed area to
     ensure you always see the area of the sample in which you're currently
     scratching on.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     I have not backported the new code to the old gtk+ 1.2 - so this release no
     longer builds with gtk+ 1.2 - you have to upgrade to gtk+ Version 2 to be
     able to build terminatorX.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed a nasty gcc 3.2 compilation bug - thanks to <person>
      <name>Adam Duck</name>
      <email>duck@informatik.uni-frankfurt.de</email>
     </person> and other reporters</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.73">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed a compilation bug ocurring on big endian systems only.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed the built-in wav loading routines for big endian systems (again).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Finally traced down and fixed a long outstanding bug in the dial widget,
     the background of the dials is now drawn correctly.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Ported terminatorX to gtk+ Version 2. The code for gtk2 will be enabled
     when gtk2 is detected by configure. To force terminatorX to use the good
     old gtk 1.2.x (x>=5) run configure with the '--disable-gtk2' switch.
     WARNING: gdkxft-users: gtk2 applications segfault when preloading
     libgdk_xft.so! So unset LD_PRELOAD and set GDK_USE_XFT=1 instead.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Applied a patch from Adrian that brings lots of new stuff:<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        Debian package support (removed - Mike Furr now maintains an official
        Debain package for terminatorX)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        enhanced GNOME integration</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        a manpage for terminatorX</para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Included another gcc3 fix thanks to <person>
      <name>Gregor Riepl</name>
      <email>seto-kun@freesurf.ch></email>
     </person></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Improved configure's compatibilty - it should detect pthreads more reliably
     and it should detect ladspa.h when located in /usr/local/include without
     /usr/local/include being contained in the include path.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     This release should compile and run on FreeBSD systems and possibly
     OpenBSD, too. Thanks for help and testing this goes to <person>
      <name>Tilman Linneweh</name>
      <email>tilman@arved.de</email>
     </person>.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Sequencer now refuses to play when no events available - and displays a
     dialog that suggests running the audio engine.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     De-uglified the terminatorX note dialog.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed gtk+2 signals for load file dialog</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Pre-listen support for mpg321</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Added a new auto-hiding "panel-bar" to which turntable control and audio
     panels can be minimized to.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Cleaned up the turntables' audio panel for better looks and easier usage</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Rewrote the engine thread completely - unlike before the engine thread is
     created on startup and kept alive until termination.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     terminatorX can now be run suid root - and it might even be safe. After
     creating the engine thread both terminatorX threads drop root privileges
     before evaluating any parameters or reading/writing files, etc. The problem
     is the pthread "manager thread" is out of control of terminatorX code - so
     I cannot tell that thread to drop privileges.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed Drag'n'Drop for GNOME 2</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     To enhance the loading of audiofiles terminatorX now contains code to use
     mad (MPEG Audio Decoder), libvorbis and libaudiofile directly instead of
     pipeing audio data through mpg123, ogg123 or sox. As a result the new
     routines bring following advantages:<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        tX loads audiofiles significantly faster</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        tX now honours the samplerate of an audiofile (by adjusting the pitch of
        the turntable)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        tX provides much better feedback on the loading progress</para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>Although the old loading-methods are still available (and piped loading has been
     improved, too) I highly recommend installing the libraries above as the new
     routines simply work better.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Deleted tons of old outdated code in tX_engine.cc and tX_mastergui.cc</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.72">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Applied a patch from <person>
      <name>Matthew Evans</name>
      <email>activesx@hotmail.com</email>
     </person> that introduces support for Ogg Vorbis audiofiles. It requires ogg123 > RC2 and
     sox to work. Autodetection is supported via configure (--enable-ogg123).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Experimental support for input devices other than the core-pointer under
     XFree86 > 4. This uses the xsetpointer executable that comes with XFree86.
     configure should autodetect this correctly, in case it doesn't use the
     --enable-xetpointer switch.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Adrian sent me a patch introducing two new buttons: mute and solo. As it
     didn't fully harmonize with the sequencer I rewrote parts of it and added
     new functionality to the turntables: They can now be switched to mix_solo
     or mix_mute - these settings affect current mixing only - their values will
     neither be saved nor will changes to those control be recorded in the
     sequencer - if you want to record muting events either use the mute button
     from the turntable's trigger menu, the keyboard short-cuts (alt/strg), or
     your middle mouse button.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed a bug that produced corrupt wavfiles on big endian machines</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     some minor fixes to make terminatorX compile with newer gcc releases</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Well, I am allowed to change my mind, aren't I? Anyway, 3DNow! is back.
     Nevertheless newer gcc releases seem to have a bug in handling movq and the
     current 3DNow! stereo implementation does not seem to be very efficient. So
     use --enable-3dnow only if you want to help me improve perfomance.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Modified the mpg123 loader in order to make it work with mpg321, too.
     mpg321 lacks support for mpg123's -m switch ("singlemix") therefor mpg?2?'s
     output is now piped into sox to convert the signal to mono. For this reason
     mpg?2? support now requires sox to be installed, too.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added a workaround for a gtk+ bug that causes empty labels when strings
     contain umlauts - unluckily my name features one of these so I had to write
     this workaround.</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.71">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     applied a big patch from <person>
      <name>Adrian Reber</name>
      <email>adrian@lisas.de</email>
     </person>. This patch includes:<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        compile fixes for the newer gcc releases</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        enhancements to the commandline switches (try --help for more details)</para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     the bigNewThang (TM) is STEREO output. The Pan-Buttons now actually do what
     you'd expect them to. Therefore your soundcard must have stereo support of
     course but I guess in 2001 this really shouldn't be a problem, right? The
     recorded wavfiles will now be stereo wavfiles of course. Note that stereo
     output means double audio-bandwith, so if you tuned your old terminatorX
     setup to smallest latency you might get clicks now. You can easily fix this
     by increasing the buffer size in the options dialog by one - this will
     result in the same latency as before btw.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The echo effect has undergone some enhancements to profit from the new
     stereo output. It's signal will now be mixed seperately so you can choose a
     different stereo panorama position for the echo signal. So the new echo
     effect now features it's own PAN-knob. This does have some sideeffects
     though, for more details on this check the manual. Additionally the echo
     effect now has it's own volume setting to influence the dry/wet ratio of
     this effect.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Some LADSPA effects tend to create NAN (Not A Number) float values under
     certain conditions. This is bad as all following operations will result in
     NANs, so there will be no audio output no more. Now I will not introduce
     code to check for NANs as this is a waste of CPU-power, producing NANs is
     IMHO a faulty behaviour for LADSPA plugins and it should be fixed in there.
     Now a problem with the previous release was that the echo and lowpass
     effects "ate" those NANs resulting in NANs in those effects' buffers. So
     once a NAN got in there these effects caused the whole audio output to mute
     (forever). Which is why I now introduced some code to clear the buffers in
     echo and lowpass whenever you dis- and reenable them.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The GUI does have two master vu-meters now. The turntable's still have one
     vu-meter only. Note that the echo-signal is *not* included in the
     turntable's vu-meter now, as it's mixed seperately.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The 3DNow!-Optimizations are gone. And they'll proabably never come back as
     I don't have time to maintain the same algorithm twice.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The documentation has been updated to meet the new features. A lot of typos
     have been fixed as well.</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.70">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     this list may be incomplete</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     This release brings support for LADSPA plugins. These plugins can be
     inserted into any turntable's effect chain at any position. You can edit
     the the effect sequence with the two tiny blue arrows. The builtin effects
     reside in the same effect chain as LADSPA plugins, but unlike LADSPA
     plugins they cannot be removed (nor multi-instanciated). The LADSPA plugins
     have to "fit" into the effect chain, which is why terminatorX supports
     *mono* plugins (plugins that have one audio-in and one audio-out port)
     only. For the plugin's control ports, termintatorX supports all HINTS
     except for LADSPA_HINT_LOGARITHMIC. Some control ports might be hard to
     handle as LAPDSA control ports can have very wide value ranges. It is
     possible to enter precise values though. Get LADSPA and the CMT plugins
     from <link ref="http://www.ladspa.org">http://www.ladspa.org</link>.
	 All parameters for LADSPA-plugins are "sequencable parameters", so you can
     record parameter-change events for the plugin's knobs just as for the
     standard parameters.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     GUI re-design to support dynamic plugin GUIs. The audiofile-display is now
     seperated from the turntable's controls. The groups are split in to panels
     which can be minimized if not required (orange arrow). The panels'
     minimized-status will be saved within the set files. To add a plugin effect
     into the turntables effect chain click on the "FX"- button and choose the
     plugin of your choice. To get more info on the plugin effects click on
     their panel's label. NOTE: The panning-control is not working yet. It'll
     work as soon as stereo is done.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     As always when introducing something new, the set-file file-format has
     changed.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The parameter-to-mouse-axis mapping has been moved from hardcoded to
     dynamic. You can now map any parameter that's considered "mappable" to the
     mouse-axis of your choice (for each turntable separately). This is true for
     the control ports of LADSPA-plugins, too.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     <person>
      <name>Josh Steiner</name>
      <email>joschi@eds.org</email>
     </person> has joined terminatorX development. For this release he has added some startup
     parameters for terminatorX, some of them aiming for future MIDI support,
     and therefor not functional yet. Run "terminatorX --help" to get more
     details.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     I know write the "manual" in SGML with the DocBook DTD. The distribution
     contains the HTML and the postscript version. These transformation have
     been created using James Clark's jade (DSSSL-processor) and Norman Walsh's
     DSSSL stylesheets for DocBook.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Removed obsolete "number of vtts"-option from the options dialog.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Applied a patch from Josh that fixes running the soundfile editor for files
     including a blank in their filename.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     New tooltips for the complete GUI.</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.61" unreleased="true">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     applied a tiny patch from <person>
      <name>Atsushi Yamagata</name>
      <email>yamagata@plathome.co.jp</email>
     </person> to set locale on startup.</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.60">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     terminatorX has a sequencer now. Warning: with the current design the
     sequencer will correctly play back recorded events only when the buffer
     size (of the audio device) is set to the same size as it was when recording
     the events. I know this is annoying and I will try to find a solution to
     this. Please take a look at the README to find out how the sequencer works.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed a bug causing the lowpass filter produce a constant signal</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed the load file / drag'n'drop segfault bug</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed the prelisten zombie processes bug</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed the segfault on termination bug (with the audio engine running)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     hacked the mixer code to use 3DNow! too. This improves 3DNow! performance
     gain from previously ~6% to more than 20% (depending on compiler
     optimizations)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     extended the set-file-format to allow storing of sequencer events. This
     release allows loading old tX-sets too.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     some gui icons. Choose Text/Icon / Icon only / Text only display of these
     icons in the Options dialog. You'll have to restart tX to see the changes
     though.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     "soundfile-editor support": Enter the soundfile-editor of your choice in
     the tX-Options dialog (Still looking for an editor? Checkout Dave's Linux
     Sound and MIDI Pages: http://www.bright.net/~dlphilp/linuxsound/). Click
     the edit button in the Main-Panel to start your editor with the turntable's
     soundfile - edit ;) - save and click the reload button.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     big endian bug fixes by <person>
      <name>Scott C. Knight</name>
      <email>scknight@indiana.edu</email>
     </person></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     --enable-benchmark will now produce a benchmark binary. This takes a set
     file as a parameter (that set file should autotrigger all tables, else the
     benchmark will measure how fast tX can generate zeros ;) WARNING: the
     benchmark binary is not a usable terminatorX binary.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     a new dial-widget. I created this for the upcoming GUI-redesign - and
     decided I let you debug it right now ;) If you don't want it run configure
     with the --disable-dial switch.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     some gui redesign. The volume scales are now located near their
     corresponding "flash"-widget. This release fits into very small windows -
     so it should be usable on smaller displays as well.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Adrian told me configure doesn't have to check for glib after checking for
     gtk+ - I guess he's right so the glib-test has gone.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     more minor fixes</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.55">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     implemented "sequenceable parameters" (see tX_seqpar.*). This means the
     groundwork for the sequencer is done. Although this release does not yet
     feature a sequencer - there's still a profit: you can now see the GUI (e.g.
     the lowpass-freq slider) update while you change that value with your mouse
     in dga grab mode (e.g. up/down with the default X/Y-Control settings).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed (libmmx) mmx.h to work with gcc 2.95 and above</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed compilation problems for big endian machines. still runtime probs
     reported though.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed configure-script as the new bash complains about == in string
     compares</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed some gui segfaults</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added an ugly GNOME-mimetype installer. This installs the ".tX"-mime type,
     an terminatorX-application icon and a ".tX"-icon. I could use some hints on
     how I could make automake install that instead of an extra script. (see
     README.GNOME)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added Drag'n Drop support. Works with the great gmc. Drop an audio file
     over the filename-button or the wavdisplay of a turntable to load it into
     that table. Drop an audiofile over the "Add Turntable" Button to create a
     new turntable and load that file into that turntable. Drop a tX-set file
     over the "Load Set" button to load the set.</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.51">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixes the load_piped() compilation error if you use neither sox nor mpg123.
     Note that you have no "pre-listening" without mpg123 for mp3s and no
     "pre-listening" for any other file without sox.</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.5">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Yet another redesign ;) Oh well this project moved from c++/multithreaded
     to c++/singlethreaded, to c/multithreaded and now, finally, back to
     c++/multithreaded. This shows quite some foresight, I'd say ;)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Due to the redesign I had to change a lot (everything?) again so this
     document can impossibly hold all changes. but let's see:</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     tX now uses floats instead of doubles for a lot of parameters. Therefore
     the old .terminatorXrc.bin is now called .terminatorX3rc.bin to allow
     parallel use of older releases. But you'll have to configure the new
     release again the first time you run it.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     tX now supports an unlimited no of turntables. The only limit is your
     display really.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Each of these turntables has their own pitch / volume settings and a
     dedicated lowpass and echo effect section.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     You can now map mouse motion to a function of your choice (scratching/
     volume/cutoff/echo-feedback and nothing)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Recording will now happen straight to disk. You'll have to specify a
     filename before you start recording.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     You can sync the turntables to one master turntable.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     There are two master settings for pitch and volume available to modify all
     turntables. The turntable pitch is relative to the master pitch.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     You can save a complete set (of turntables and settings) to a .tX set file.
     The audiofile data will *not* be saved within that file, but it'll contain
     the absolut filename to these files. I know this makes the act of
     exchanging sets over the net more complex so if somebody wants to code set
     files with integrated audio data... ;)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The way audiofiles are loaded has been redesigned too: the builtin wav
     routines, the sox support and mpg123 are no longer connected. This means
     you can use mpg123 support without sox support and still have the builtin
     wav routines enabled. If you have the builtin wav reader and sox enabled,
     tX will try try to use the builtin routines first, and if they fail sox
     will be used as a fallback which is of course slower as you know... There's
     some support for Benno Senoner's brilliant 3.2-mmap() patch but the patch
     still needs to be ported.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     You can now select which parameter to map to a mouse axis.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     experimental 3DNow! support (works with gcc &lt; 2.95 only)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     tX-windows now have an icon, thanks Michael!</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.2">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     implemented 2D-Scratching ;) You can now use the other axis of your mouse
     two modify the cutoff frequency of the lowpass filter (if enabled). The
     resonance factor can be set via the slider underneath "LP Filter". Seems to
     eat quite some CPU power though...</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Updated THANKS, AUTHORS</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     as most people seem to use sox/mpg123 anyway and as I still get "I want
     mp3" emails I changed the configure script slightly: It now automatically
     enables the use of sox and mpg123 if these are available. If you still want
     'em good old 16Bit/44.1Khz/Mono builtin routines you have to specify
     --enable-wavonly with your configure cmdline.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Prepared the tarball for the Win32 port. You can now compile tX with cygwin
     and the Makefile.cygwin in the src directory if you have all the required
     libs (gtk, pthreads etc...). The resulting exe will run BUT is completely
     unusable for now... <person>
      <name>Stou Sandalski</name>
      <email>tangui@cell2000.net</email>
     </person> and I are planning to make it usable in the future.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     The About-Dialog now contains some info on how the binary was compiled</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.1">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Optimized audio-rendering code for speed (might run on some machines with
     smaller buffsize (-> lower latency) than pre-3.1) - Hey, tX now uses less
     than 10% CPU (says kpm) with mixing enabled on my i586-200MMX machine!!</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     &quot;fixed&quot; stdout-output. Due to the pipe-buffering realtime
     schratching can not be considered usable for now :(</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Added config option --enable-scheduler, which will cause the terminatorX
     engine-thread to run with FIFO scheduling policy and highest priority. This
     might enable some machines to use smaller buffsizes. It requries root
     privileges though - either run terminatorX as root - or make terminatorX
     suid root WHICH IS A BAD IDEA FOR MULTI-USER SYSTEMS IF OTHER USERS CAN
     ACCESS THE BINARY ;) You only have to think about this when you experience
     buffer underruns with your desired latency. And it might not even help...</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Rehacked the de-clicking (fading) code. The old one tried to be much more
     intelligent - and failed fading out the signal sometimes. The new code is
     much simpler (faster) and is much more reliable.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added common sense to the warp feature (f-key in scratch mode). The warping
     speed is still connected to the mouse speed but it's now adjusted to the
     sample size as well: you can warp through any sample completely with the
     same mouse distance.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added debug configure switch. Enables (very few) debug messages for now. I
     decided not to enable the old V2.X messages as they are sent to stdout,
     which would sound pretty strange to people who use the stdout-option.</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.02">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed Adrian's name in the THANKS file. Sorry, Adrian.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Corrected Makefile.am for license.c that did not build correctly on some
     systems - Thanks to <person>
      <name>Michael Pruett</name>
      <email>mikep@ugcs.caltech.edu</email>
     </person></para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.01">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     fixed a bug that caused terminatorX to crash without --enable-sox or
     mpg123input.</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="3.0">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Changed everything ;)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     switched from C++ to C for gtk's sake</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     switched back two multithreading</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     implemented new gtk+ gui and dialogs</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     new mouse-sampling code now uses DGA's DirectMouse</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     implemented "initalizing"-support for XInput devices.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     new (alpha) "pre-listening" feature in scratch/loop dialogs</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     hacked vtt for click-free audio. Might be problematic with big kernel level
     buffersizes but scratching with big buffsize is no fun anyway.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     options are now stored in ~/.terminatorXrc.bin automatically (on exit) as
     well as windowsize and the last used filenames</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     terminatorX now comes with a configure script - no more Makefile hacking
     required (nor a good idea ;) )</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     new wavdisplay-widget update frequency is now configureable</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     new position-display is much more visible which allows more precise
     scratching</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     new mute-feature allows you to silence the scratch-playback completely
     while the loop keeps playing (press either &lt;m&gt;-key or right
     mouse-button.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     support for mouse buttons:<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        1. (left) button: same as &lt;SPACE&gt;, do scratch</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        2. (right) button: mute scratch</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para class="screen">
        3. (middle) button: stop</para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     wrote support for sox and mpg123. This enables terminatorX to read close to
     any audiofile. You need to have sox and mp3 and this feature (as it is
     still alpha) needs to be enabled via configure-switches see INSTALL</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     licmak now is an awk script. Thanks Christian! I was also received two perl
     scripts (Thanks, guys!) but I now use the awk script as it is the smallest.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     introduced &lt;F&gt;-key to "warp" through scratch-sample (just check it
     out)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     dropped commandline arguments</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     dropped old X-Code + Mouse warping madness</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     bug fixes (less than bug introduces though ;) )</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="2.4" unreleased="true">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     implemented a time counter</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     licmak now finally is what it should be: a perl script (licmak.pl) it was
     contributed by <person>
      <name>Adam SjMAKE_THIS_OSLASHgren</name>
      <email>asjo@diku.dk</email>
     </person>. Thanks!</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="2.3">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     wavfile overreading fixed by <person>
      <name>Andrew C. Bul+hac?k</name>
      <email>acb@zikzak.net</email>
     </person></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Using portable type definitions now where required. If you don't have a
     &lt;sys/types.h&gt; on your system and your machines type sizes equal those
     of an X86-machine you can specify -DUSE_X86_TYPES in Makefile to compile
     without &lt;sys/types.h&gt;</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Slight change in audiodevice-handling that fixes improper buffsize settings
     on some soundcards (e.g. GUS)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Implemented "keep device open"-feature. Needs to be enabled via the
     -DKEEP_DEV_OPEN switch in Makefile</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Added some comments to the Makefile for easier editing</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Added Big Endian support. Use -DBIG_ENDIAN_MACHINE for big endian hosts
     like ultrapenguin suns or linux ppc. There's also -DBIG_ENDIAN_AUDIO for
     big endian audio hardware (rare?) available, although proabably nobody will
     need this.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Changed mix behaviour: Mix is now automatically turned on on startup if the
     user has specified a proper loop file. (with the --loop or -l switch)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     New mixing routine. You can now set the loop to scratch volume ratio with
     the cursor keys (left/right). If you modify the volumes while recording
     these action's will not be recorded. Saving happens with the currently set
     level.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Fixed README-Bug said &lt;m&gt; instead of &lt;x&gt;</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="2.2">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     first released version</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added colors, more standard use of X11</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added loop support</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added statusbar with mode/status display</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added commandline options and help (on usage and keys)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added raw/mixed save scratch feature</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added licmak to include license into binary</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     new handling of XAutoRepeat, only turned off now when SPACE pressed</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     modified wave display (faster + nicer + incorrect (who cares anyway))</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     Makefile fixed by <person>
      <name>Adrian Reber</name>
      <email>adrian@lisas.de</email>
     </person></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     bug fixes</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="2.1" unreleased="true">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     added recording, playback of recording functionality</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="2.0" unreleased="true">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     moved from multithreaded to singlethreaded</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     position feedback</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     bug fixes</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="1.0" unreleased="true">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     mouse support</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     no more position display due to pthread/X probs</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     bug fixes</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
  <version name="0.5" unreleased="true">
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     first version</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     no mouse handling</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     accelerating vtt via sinus</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     multithreaded</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para class="screen">
     sound aliasing</para>
   </listitem>
  </version>
 </changelog>
</section>
