<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "./tX.dtd">
<section name="main">
  <main>
    <general>
      <heading>Welcome to the terminatorX website!</heading>
      <subtitle>
	<nopara>Bookmark this site as <link ref="http://www.terminatorX.cx">
	    www.terminatorX.cx</link>. It's located on
	  <link ref="http://42.fht-esslingen.de">42.fht-esslingen.de</link>
	</nopara>
      </subtitle>
      <text>
	<para>
	  For those of you who drop by for the first time: terminatorX is a
	  realtime audio synthesizer that allows you to "scratch" on digitally
	  sampled audio data (*.wav, *.au, *.ogg, *.mp3, etc.) the way hiphop-DJs
	  scratch on vinyl records. It features multiple turntables, realtime
	  effects (buit-in as well as
	  <link ref="http://www.ladspa.org">LADSPA</link> plugin
	  effects), a sequencer and MIDI interface - all accessible through 
	  an easy-to-use gtk+ GUI. <bold>This sofware is designed to run
	    under Linux, FreeBSD and the like</bold>. <!-- It will possibly run und
	  other UNIXish systems running
	  <link ref="http://www.xfree86.org">XFree86</link> and a
	  compatilbe audio device, like OpenBSD. -->
	  If you have more questions read the <link
          ref="faq.html">FAQ</link>/<link ref="doc/index.html">Manual</link>/<link
          ref="http://www.boosthardware.com/LAU/quicktoots/toots/tx_toot/tx_toot1.html">Tutorial</link>/<link 
	  ref="COPYING">LICENSE</link> and if you have further questions, suggestions,
	  patches, <link ref="scratches.html">scratches</link> send me a
	  <link ref="mailto:alex@lisas.de">mail</link>
	</para>
      </text>
    </general>

    <news>
    <newsitem>
    	<newsheader date="April 03"><link ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX 3.80</link> and <link ref="aseqjoy.html">aseqjoy 0.0.1</link></newsheader>
	<newstext>
		<para>This terminatorX release does a very good job at erasing points from my TODO-for-4.0 list. Among
		other things this release introduces:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>Finally terminatorX has a <bold>native</bold> <link ref="http://www.alsa-project.org">ALSA</link> 
			<bold>backend</bold>. See the new <italic>Preferences</italic> dialog and the online manual for details. 
			The ALSA and the OSS backends now both support operating at an 
			<bold>arbitrary sampling rate</bold>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>The audio data display is now <bold>zoomable</bold>. This helps scratching large audio
			files (like complete songs) significantly. Use the slider on the right of the display area to adjust
			the zoom level. When playing the audio data will scroll in such a manner that the current position
			is always centered.
			</para>
			<para>To optimize playback performance terminatorX does a lot of "zoom" calculations in
			advance - so adjusting the slider will cause quite some amount of recalculation on large audio
			files.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem><para>A <bold>MIDI interface</bold> thanks to a patch by
			<person><name>Arthur Peters</name><email>amp@singingwizard.org</email></person>. The MIDI interface 
			is based upon the <link ref="http://www.alsa-project.org">ALSA</link> sequencer API, so you'll
			have to connect terminatorX' input port to an output port of your choice with either <screen>aconnect</screen>
			or for example the <link ref="http://pkl.net/~node/alsa-patch-bay.html">alsa-patch-bay</link>. To map a MIDI controller or note events
			to a turntable's parameter click the <italic>MIDI Mapping</italic> button.
			</para>
			<para>In order to test the new interface I hacked a little tool called 
			<link ref="aseqjoy.html">aseqjoy</link> that emits MIDI controller messages based on
			Joystick motion.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem><para>I finally untied audio rendering and audio backend. terminatorX now operates
			at a <bold>fixed internal blocksize</bold> of 1 ms. So now it doesn't matter anymore with which blocksize
			events were recorded - they will be played back correctly with any audio device blocksize.</para>
			<para>Note that
			a minor problem remains: the sampling rate has an effect on the blocksize, too. While there is 
			no problem switching from 22 or 32 kHz to 48 kHz, there will be a slight rounding error switching from or
			to 44.1 kHz. So if you record and playback events I suggest you keep the sampling rate the same,
			or use "straight" sampling rates like 22, 32 and 48 kHz only.
			</para></listitem>
			
			<listitem>
			<para>I added a little pitch calculator that allows adjusting the playback speed
			of a turntable to that of the master turntable. Click the <screen>Pitch Adj.</screen>
			button for more details.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			
			<listitem>
			<para>Advancing the use of XML: many XML-related bugs have been fixed, and I moved the <bold>set file format
			to XML</bold>, too. The MIDI mappings of parameters will be stored within set files, too. As XML set files
			with a lot of sequencer events can grow quite big tX supports writing <bold>gzip compressed set files</bold>
			through the use of <link ref="http://www.zlib.org">zlib</link>.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>Thanks to a suggestion by
				<person><name>Darrick Servis</name><email>darrick@dcn.davis.ca.us</email></person> 
				terminatorX <bold>no longer clips audio</bold>. If the generated amplitude goes beyond the maximum
				it will simply be cut off.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>Further cleaning up the layout for small DJ laptop displays: moved some buttons to
			a <bold>menu bar</bold> to waste less space. Addtionally you can now hit <screen>F11</screen> to
			enter <bold>fullscreen</bold> mode - if your window manager supports <italic>NETWM</italic>.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem><para>Dropped support for the old gtk+ 1.2 - you have to use gtk+ &gt;= 2.0, now.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</newstext>
    </newsitem>
      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="18 Sep"><link ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX
	    V3.73</link> available, 
	  <link ref="http://www.debian.org">Debian</link> inclusion +
	  a <link ref="http://www.boosthardware.com/LAU/quicktoots/toots/tx_toot/tx_toot1.html">tutorial</link>
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
	  <para>Aside of fixing numerous bugs, the new release does have
	    some new features:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>I ported terminatorX to <link ref="http://www.gtk.org">gtk+</link>
		  <bold>Version 2</bold> so tX should integrate nicely
		  with your GNOME 2 desktop. This release still builds with
		  the old gtk+ 1.2, too, but I don't plan to support it
		  much longer.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	 
	    <screenshot filename="shot-3.73-1.png">
	      <nopara>Minimizing controls to save space</nopara>
	    </screenshot>
	 
	  <itemizedlist>	      
	      <listitem>
		<para>I reworked the GUI a bit in order to make
		  terminatorX fit better on those small DJ-laptop
		  displays. Audio and control panels can now be minimized to 
		  a <bold>panel bar</bold> to save space - works just like
		  GNOME's window list. The panel bar status is
		  stored within setfiles and restored upon
		  loading. Additionally the buttons of the audio panel have
		  been restructured. To lighten up the GUI five
		  buttons have been merged into <bold>two</bold> - on
		  clicking one of these you'll get a popup menu with all
		previous functionality.
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		After spending an evening with Adrian in front of his
		big endian system fixing the audiofile loading
		routines, I decided that loading audiofiles through a
		pipe is an ugly hack. Therefor I wrote <bold>three new audiodfile
		loading methods</bold> that utilize libraries instead of pipes. These
		are <link ref="http://www.mars.org/home/rob/proj/mpeg/">
		  mad</link> (for mp3 files), 
		<link ref="http://www.xiph.org/ogg/vorbis/">libvorbis</link>
		(for OGG/Vorbis files) and 
		<link ref="http://www.68k.org/~michael/audiofile/">
		  libaudiofile</link> (for wav/aiff/au etc.). Using these
		routines instead of the old ones brings the following
		advantages:
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>loading audiofiles is significantly <bold>faster</bold></para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>terminatorX now evaluates the <bold>sample rate</bold> of an
		      audiofile and adjusts the turntable's pitch
		      accordingly (this does not affect the regular
		      &quot;pitch&quot; setting btw)
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>the new routines provide much better <bold>visual
		      feedback</bold> on the loading progress
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		Additionally more file formats are supported, so I
		strongly recommend installing the libraries mentioned
		above to improve terminatorX' usabilty.
	      </para>	      
	    </listitem>
	      <listitem>
	      <para>Slowly approaching terminator<bold>XML</bold>: the
		  configuration file (now <italic>~/.terminatorXrc</italic>)
		  is no longer binary but an XML document. This is necessary
		  to become more flexible in the future - and it allows
		  editing your terminatorX configuration with a text editor - if
		  you want to. Of course, terminatorX now requires
		  <link ref="http://www.libxml.org">libxml</link> to be installed. For
		  convenience this release still reads the old binary config
		  and stores it as an XML document on exit. I plan to move
		  the set file format to XML soon, too.
		</para>
	      </listitem>	      
	      <listitem>
		<para>I completely rewrote the <italic>tX_engine</italic> in
		  order to allow installing terminatorX <bold>suid
		    root</bold>. This way terminatorX can run with
		  realtime scheduling policy even for unprivileged
		  users. Right after creation of the engine thread
		  terminatorX drops root privileges - so it might even
		  be safe to install terminatorX suid root - but I'll
		  leave that up to security experts to decide. For a
		  more detailed discussion read 
		<link ref="faq.html#11">this FAQ entry</link>.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Playing around with the wonderful 
		<link ref="http://www.povray.org">povray</link> a bit I
		came up with a new logo for terminatorX. The icons have
		been replaced, too - the new ones should be easier for
		your desktop perception.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Thanks to
		  <person><name>Adrian</name><email>adrian@lisas.de</email>
		  </person> terminatorX now has a <bold>manpage</bold>.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    A lot of bug fixing went into this release, too, most notably:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>An old clipping bug in the <italic>tX_dial</italic> widget code has
		been fixed.
	      </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>This release builds, runs and loads audiofiles on big endian architectures.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>terminatorX should now build from scratch not only
		on Linux but on FreeBSD, too. Thanks to <person>
		  <name> Tilman Linneweh</name><email>tilman@arved.de</email></person>
		  for testing.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Many other fixes.
	      </para>
	    </listitem> 
	  </itemizedlist>
	    Have a look at the <link ref="ChangeLog">ChangeLog</link>
	    for more details and grab the tarball or the RPMS from the 
	    <link ref="download.html#Current Version">download
	      section</link>.
	  </para>
	  <para>Aside of the release I'd like to bring to your attention
	    that 
	    <person><name>Mike
		Furr</name><email>mfurr@debian.org</email></person> 
	    is now maintainer of the
	    <link ref="http://packages.debian.org/unstable/sound/terminatorx.html">
	      terminatorX Debian package</link>. So if you're a Debian
	    user you may want to <italic>apt-get</italic> this release -
	    if you install <italic>unstable</italic> packages at all and
	    when your local mirror has been updated.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    For new terminatorX users 
	    <person><name>Brian</name><email>bredfern@calarts.edu</email></person>
	    has created a wonderful step-by-step 
	    <link ref="http://www.boosthardware.com/LAU/quicktoots/toots/tx_toot/tx_toot1.html">
	      &quot;terminatorX TOOT&quot; tutorial</link> - reading that will accelerate
	    the creation of your first scratch considerably.
	  </para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>
      
      <newsitem>
      	<newsheader date="31 Jul"><link ref="turntable.html">Turntable gallery</link> online and a fresh
	<link ref="scratches.html">scratch</link>
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
		<para>
		I finally managed to hack the website's DTD and XSLT stylesheet to support
		the <link ref="turntable.html">users' turntable section</link>. Now that it's easy
		to update, please keep these turntable images coming in! I'd really like
		to see more of your turntables.
		</para>
		<para><person><name>Brian</name><email>bredfern@calarts.edu</email></person> - 
		a California based terminatorX DJ - has contributed a very cool scratch
		for the <link ref="scratches.html">scratches section</link>. It's just an
		excerpt of a complete drum and bass set that is available at Brian's 
		 <link ref="http://asapien.org">website</link> - which seems to be down currently.
		 In case it doesn't come up again I'll mirror the complete set here, too.
		</para>
		<para>
		<italic>The names have been changed to protect the innocent...</italic> from
		<bold>spamming</bold>. The XSLT stylesheet now mangles all email addresses
		on this site except for mine - if you've seen a correct email address before
		you should be able to recover the real address easily. BTW if you're a spam
		victim, too, add the incredible <link ref="http://spamassassin.org">spamassassin</link>
		to your <italic>.procmailrc</italic> and spam won't annoy you anymore.
		</para>
		<para>On terminatorX news Version 3.73 should be ready for release RSN! It will
		probably still lack native ALSA support, though.
		</para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>
      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="05 jan">happy new year: 
	  <link ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX V3.72</link> is here.
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
	  <para>
	    Hope everybody had a nice start into 2002, these are the changes
	    that come with terminatorX release 3.72 
	    (for details check the <link ref="ChangeLog">ChangeLog</link>):
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Thanks to a patch from <person>
		    <name>Matthew Evans</name>
		    <email>activesx@hotmail.com</email>
		  </person>
		    terminatorX finally supports loading
		    <link ref="http://www.vorbis.com">Ogg Vorbis</link>
		    audiofiles. Note that this feature requires ogg123
		    (>= RC2)
		    and <link
		    ref="http://sox.sourceforge.net">sox</link>
		    installed. The very fresh RC3 release of Ogg Vorbis
		    works just fine, too.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><person><name>Adrian</name>
		    <email>adrian@lisas.de</email></person> once again
		    submitted code to the project: terminatorX now
		    features <bold>mute</bold> and <bold>solo</bold>
		    buttons for each turntable's mixing unit. The
		    initial patch had some problems with the already
		    existing mute-function in terminatorX, therefor I
		    extended the turntable in such a way that the new
		    buttons <bold>only affect current mixing</bold> -
		    the sequencer will not record any events for them.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>I updated the XInput code to work with XFree86 >
		  4. terminatorX now uses the
		  <italic>xsetpointer</italic> binary that comes with 
		  XFree86 to switch the core pointer - as the old code
		  doesn't work with newer XFree86 releases anymore. 
		  <italic>configure</italic> should auto-detect 
		  <italic>xsetpointer</italic> if it's available.
		  <bold>Note:</bold> You only need to specify an
		  additional XInput Device in the options dialog if you
		  want to use a scratching device other than your
		  mouse. (Yeah, I know, I state that in the docs,
		  tooltips, everywhere - but I still get bug reports
		  related to that issue...)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Updated mpg123 loading routines that should work
		  with <link ref="http://mpg321.sourceforge.net">mpg321</link>
		  (which many distros install instead of
		  mpg123 these days), too. Note that you'll have to have 
		  <link ref="http://sox.sourceforge.net">sox</link>
		  installed in order to get mp3-loading to work (As
		  mpg321 doesn't support mpg123's <italic>-m</italic>
		  switch).
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>fixes for misc bugs (writing broken .wav's on big
		endian machines, gcc >= 3.x compile fixes, some gtk+
		cleanups, etc.)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	  <para>Grab the sources or the fresh RPMs (Thanks,  
	    <person><name>Adrian</name><email>adrian@lisas.de</email>
	    </person>!) from the <link ref="download.html#Current Version">download
	    section</link>.
	  </para>
	  <para>Initially I planned to integrate native <link
	  ref="http://www.alsa-project.org">ALSA</link>-support into
	  this release but I simply failed to finish. As many people 
	  wanted to have some of the above features early I decided to
	  release it without ALSA now, as I'll be busy for the upcomming 
	  weeks. I haven't given up on ALSA though, hopefully the next
	  terminatorX release will feature a new audiodevice backend
	  that supports ALSA (V0.9) <bold>and</bold> OSS and brings many 
	  other adtvantages.
	  </para>
	  <para>The website has undergone minor updates, too:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>The section header's now should look fine with
		  <link
		  ref="http://www.mozilla.org">Mozilla</link>-based
		  browsers. They might look funny with older netscapes, though.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Updated the 
		  <link ref="screenshots.html">screenshots</link> as
		  people started asking howto achieve that old tX V3.5
		  layout :)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Minor fixes to make <link ref="http://www.w3.org">W3C</link>'s validator accept the
		pages again, and a favicon that needs some improvement.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>
       
<!--      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="20 jun">New scratches, turntables &amp; FAQ updates
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
	  <para>Hey, it seems that the <link ref="turntable.html">turntable
	      section</link> inspires quite some of you to build your own
	    tX-turntables - which is <bold>really cool</bold>! So I plan to
	    provide an additional <italic>users' turntables</italic>-section
	    ASAP. Now <person><name>Fernando</name>
	      <email>ffabreti@yahoo.com.br</email>
	    </person> not only sent me a cool
	    fresh <link ref="aint.mp3">scratch</link> you can grab from the
	    <link ref="scratches.html">users' scratches-section</link> but also
	    pictures from his turntable. Take a look at his turntable
	    in the <link ref="fernando.html">turntable section
	    </link>. In case <bold>you</bold> built
	    your own turntable already, please
	    <link ref="mailto:alex@lisas.de">send</link>
	      me some images of it - I'm
	    really keen on seeing what your turntables look like.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <person>
	      <name>Dr. Uggs</name>
	      <email>jesset@katapultz.org</email>
	    </person> visited the <link ref="scratches.html">users'
	      scratches-section</link> a while ago, too, and decided to
	    contribute his own scratch - not created with terminatorX but a
	    <bold>real</bold> turntable. I thought this fine scratch should
	    be up here, too - not in the users' scratches section though as
	    it's not a user-scratch. So you can listen to it right
	    <link ref="earth.mp3">here</link> - it's a good chance to compare
	    a real turntable's sound against terminatorX.
	  </para>
	  <para>If you have problems getting your mouse to actually scratch
	    with terminatorX, I have some hints on this issue in the
	    <link ref="faq.html">FAQ-Section</link> now.
	  </para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>
      
      <newsitem>
        <newsheader date="22 mar">Fresh <link ref="download.html#Current Version">
            RPMs</link> (for i586 and Sparc machines)
        </newsheader>
        <newstext>   
          <para>
		The RPMs for the current release have undergone some refinement by
            <person><name>Mr. RPM</name><email>adrian@lisas.de</email></person>
		himself. In addition to updating the spec-files he built
		the current release on his very own Sparc, so there is a
		Sparc RPM available now, too.
	</para>
	<para>
		As always the RPMs are available from the 
		<link ref="download.html#Current Version">
            	download section.</link>
	</para>
        </newstext>
      </newsitem>  
 

      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="20 mar"><link ref="download.html#Current Version">
	    RPMs</link> for Version 3.71 available 
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
	  <para>Faster than ever before
	    <person><name>Adrian</name><email>adrian@lisas.de</email></person>
	    has produced the rpms for the new release. The i586 and src RPMs
	    are available from the <link ref="download.html#Current Version">
	    download section</link>. These are V4-RPMs again - if you've got
	    a problem with them read the news below (from dec 18) for
	    more details on how to install V4-RPMs on a RPM-V3 systems.
	  </para>
	  <para>Sparc-Owners may be pleased to hear that there should be RPMs
	    for their platform sometime tomorrow.
	  </para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>
      
      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="20 mar">left, right, left, right...
	  <link ref="download.html#Current Version">
	    terminatorX V3.71</link> is up.
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
	  <para>
	    Yep, a new release is here that brings the <bold>very latest</bold>
	    in HIFI technology: <italic>STEREO</italic>-operation ;) 
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    List of changes (for more details see the
	    <link ref="ChangeLog">ChangeLog</link>)
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>So tX is <bold>stereo</bold> now, producing stereo
		  output for your soundcard and recording stereo
		  wavfiles of course. The "pan" knobs for each turntable now
		  actually <italic>do something</italic>. If you had
		  terminatorX installed before you might have to
		  increase the buffer size setting to fit stereo playback.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>The new release has a patch from <person><name>Adrian
		      Reber</name><email>adrian@lisas.de</email></person>
		  applied, that fixes some issues with newer gcc releases, some
		  minor bugs and cleans up the startup switches (there are
		  some new ones, too - run <italic>terminatorX -help</italic>
		  for more details). 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>The echo effect received <bold>two new controls</bold>:
		  a pan-control - to allow positioning the echo-signal at
		  position in the stereo panorama that differs from the
		  turntable's main pan-position - and an additional volume
		  parameter for the echo-signal.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>The built-in effects now <bold>clear their buffers</bold>
		  on enabling
		  to ensure that NANs (that some LADSPA plugins may create
		  under certain conditions) do not get stuck in there.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Documentation updates and more bugfixes.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	  <para>As the handling of the echo effect is somewhat special now, I
	    used <link ref="http://www.lysator.liu.se/~alla/dia/">dia</link>
	    and
	    <link ref="http://www.gimp.org">the gimp</link> to create a little graphic
	    to clear things up a bit (the manual contains a textual
	    description, too):
	    <screenshot filename="signalflow.jpg">
	      <nopara>tX signal routing</nopara>
	    </screenshot>
	  </para>
	  <para>RPMs will be available soon.</para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>

      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="18 dec"><link ref="download.html#Current Version">
	    RPMs</link> done and some remixes.
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
	  <para>
	    <person><name>Adrian</name><email>adrian@lisas.de</email></person>
	    set me up with the rpms for Version 3.70. Note that these are
	    RPMV4-rpms designed for RedHat 7.0. If you want to use these with
	    RedHat 6.1/6.2 you'll have to upgrade to rpm-3.0.5. You can
	    download the official RedHat-rpm-updates from right here, as this
	    server mirrors the RedHat updates (<link ref="ftp://rhlx01.fht-esslingen.de/Mirrors/updates.redhat.com/6.1/i386/">6.1</link>,
	    <link ref="ftp://rhlx01.fht-esslingen.de/Mirrors/updates.redhat.com/6.2/i386/">6.2</link>). Then grab the terminatorX-3.70-rpms from the
	    <link ref="download.html#Current Version">download section</link>.
	  </para> 
	  <para>
	    <person><name>Sean</name><email>sean@frazmtn.com</email></person>
	    sent me a mail sometime ago about his
	    <link ref="http://ns.ownerguard.com/~sean/">site</link>
	    where he offers some cool remixes he made (with terminatorX). Go
	    and <link ref="http://ns.ownerguard.com/~sean/">check them
	      out</link>.
	  </para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>

      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="20 nov">It's done. 
	  <link ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX</link> V3.70
	  is here.
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
	  <para>Yeah, I know, it's been a while, and sorry to everybody I told
	    something about "two weeks", "next week" or even "tomorrow". I mean
	    at least it's here before the 2.4.0-final kernel ;)
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <screenshot filename="screenshot_v3.7.jpg">
	      <nopara>the new GUI with the plugin list popped up</nopara>
	    </screenshot>
	  </para> 
	  <para>Now, <italic>finally</italic> terminatorX <bold>Version
	      3.70</bold> is available for download. This release brings the
	    following new features:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<nopara>The most exciting new feature is <bold>LADSPA plugin
		    support</bold>. Note that this means terminatorX requires
		  the LADSPA-SDK (ladspa.h to be exact) to build. Get the
		  LADSPA-SDK from the <link ref="http://www.ladspa.org">LADSPA
		    homepage</link> (untar; cd src; make
		  install). Oh and while you're there why not grab
		  <link ref="http://www.ladspa.org/cmt/">CMT</link> and all
		  those other plugins available, too? Note that you can record
		  sequencer events for controls of LADSPA plugins just like for
		  the built-in effects.
		</nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<nopara><bold>Editable effect stack</bold>. To allow nice
		  integration of LADSPA-plugins with the built-in effects, all
		  effects now reside in the turntable's <bold>effect
		    queue</bold>. The effect-processing sequence can be edited
		  easily (with the two blue arrows). LADSPA plugins can be
		  inserted at any position in that sequence. Press the <italic>
		    FX</italic>-button to load a plugin.
		</nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<nopara>A <bold>GUI redesign</bold> again. This was necessary
		  to support dynamic addition/removal of the plugin GUIs.
		  Additionally you can now <bold>enter precise values</bold>
		  for each parameter adjustable via a dial into a
		  text entry widget alternatively. Another plus of the new GUI
		  is, that you can configure it to display only those controls
		  you want to see.
		</nopara>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<nopara>The mouse-axis-to-parameter mapping is no longer
		  hardcoded. You can now map <bold>any parameter</bold>
		  considered mappable to the mouse-axis of your choice. This
		  includes plugins' controls.
		</nopara>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<nopara>The old README has gone. I moved the info there into a
		  <bold>SGML/DocBook manual</bold>. The distribution comes with
		  the HTML and the postscript version of that manual. The HTML
		  version is available <link ref="doc/index.html">here</link>,
		  too.
		</nopara>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<nopara><bold>Tooltips</bold> for the new GUI.</nopara>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<nopara>
		  <person><name>Josh Steiner</name>
		    <email>joschi@eds.org</email></person>
		  has added some <bold>startup switches</bold> for terminatorX.
		  Try -<italic>-help</italic> for more details.</nopara>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>

	  <para>If you want to create your very own plugins without writing a
	    single line of code checkout the <italic>excellent</italic>
	    <link ref="http://www.gdam.org">GDAM</link>.
	  </para>

	  <para>Ok, now grab the new release from the
	    <link ref="download.html">download</link> section and have fun - I
	    invested quite some time in polishing so I hope there are no bigger
	    flaws in it - but you never know ;).
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    I'll put some news up here as soon as the rpms for the new release
	    are finished.
	  </para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>

      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="24 sep">website re-done &amp; some news</newsheader>
	<newstext><para>Although hardly visible this website was completely
	    re-done. I ported this site to set of XML-files and an
	    XSLT-stylesheet, as this way it should be easier to maintain. Oh
	    yeah and finally frames and gifs are gone forever.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    There might be some new bugs on this website, due to the re-design,
	    so please let me know about lousy layout in some browsers, dead
	    links or whatever, thanks!
	  </para>
	  <para>The page-contents was updated, too. People with list-linkage
	    or compile errors please take a look at the updated
	    <link ref="faq.html">FAQ</link>.
	  </para>
	  <para><bold>On terminatorX:</bold> Ok, the next release with
	    <link ref="http://www.ladspa.org">LADSPA</link>-plugin-support,
	    should be finished by next week. The GUI redesign is done, plugins
	    work nicely, just some polishing and doc-clearup is left to do.
	    Stay tuned.
	  </para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem>

      <newsitem>
	<newsheader date="12 apr">
	  terminatorX V3.60  is here and 6.000 samples
	</newsheader>
	<newstext>
	  <para>Sorry, this tarball is finished for quite some time now - but
	    I was too busy for updating.<newline/>
	    <italic>Now 3.60 is here and has some brandnew features:</italic>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><nopara>Finally the <bold>Sequencer</bold>
		  is available. You can now record/dub events for <italic>
		    scratching, volume, effects (cutoff etc.), sync settings,
		  </italic> etc. </nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara>New <bold>dial widget</bold> - I designed it
		  for the upcoming GUI redesign - but
		  I liked it so much I decided to let you betatest it right
		  now ;) -
		  configuring with -<italic>-disable-dial</italic> will give
		  you the plain gtk+ scales
		  again. </nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara>Some <bold>pixmaps</bold> for the main
		  operation buttons. These can be disabled
		  in in the Options-dialog. </nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara>Some <bold>soundfile-editor integration</bold>:
		  You can now start your favourite
		  soundfile-editor with the soundfile loaded in a turntable
		  with just one
		  click. If your looking for an soundfile editor check out
		  Dave&apos;s
		  <link ref="http://www.bright.net/~dlphilp/linuxsound/">Linux
		    Sound and Midi Pages</link></nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara><bold>Enhanced 3DNow! support</bold>: the mixer
		  routine is now 3<italic>DNow!</italic>-optimized too,
		  increasing 3DNow! performance gain from a
		  fromer 5% to more than 20%.</nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara>Big Endian support is back finally.
		  <person>
		    <name>Scott</name>
		    <email>scknight@indiana.edu</email>
		  </person> got it running on PPCs again.</nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara>Some<bold> GUI cleanups</bold>. Should now fit
		  on smaller displays, too.</nopara>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    The following <italic>long-outstanding bugs</italic> have been
	    fixed: 
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<nopara>segfault on load / drag&apos;n&apos;drop is
		  <bold>fixed</bold></nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara>zombie mpg123 and sox processes are <bold>
		    killed</bold></nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara>constant lowpass-signal <bold>fixed</bold>
		</nopara>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><nopara>and more...</nopara>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <person><name>Erik</name>
	      <email>e@osterman.com</email>
	    </person> sent me a note to inform me about his <bold>huge</bold>
	    <italic>sample-archive</italic>
	    (<link ref="http://ftp.osterman.com/pub/music/samples">http</link>/<link ref="ftp://ftp.osterman.com/pub/music/samples">ftp</link>).
	    They have more than 6.000 samples at the moment and if you want to
	    put up a mirror send him a note. 
	  </para>
	  <para>Speedy <person><name>Adrian</name>
	      <email>adrian@lisas.de</email></person> has
	    compiled the already available RPMs for V3.60. </para>
	</newstext>
      </newsitem> -->
    </news>
  </main>
</section>

