<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "./tX.dtd">
<section name="main"> &db; <main>
    <general>
      <heading>Welcome to the terminatorX website!</heading>
      <subtitle>
        <nopara>Bookmark this site as <link ref="http://terminatorX.org">terminatorX.org</link>. It's
          located on <link ref="http://42.fht-esslingen.de">42.fht-esslingen.de</link>
        </nopara>
      </subtitle>
      <text>
        <para>For those of you who drop by for the first time: terminatorX is a realtime audio
          synthesizer that allows you to &quot;scratch&quot; on digitally sampled audio data
          (*.wav, *.au, *.ogg, *.mp3, etc.) the way hiphop-DJs scratch on vinyl records. It features
          multiple turntables, realtime effects (buit-in as well as <dblink id="ladspa"/> plugin
          effects), a sequencer and MIDI interface - all accessible through an easy-to-use gtk+ GUI.
            <bold>This software is designed to run under Linux, FreeBSD and the like</bold>. If you
          have more questions read the <dblink id="faq"/>, <dblink id="manual">Manual</dblink>,
            <dblink id="tutorial">Tutorial</dblink>, <dblink id="license">License</dblink> and if
          you have further questions, suggestions, patches, <dblink
          id="scratches">scratches</dblink> send me a <link ref="mailto:alex@lisas.de">mail</link>
        </para>
      </text>
    </general>
    <news>  
	  <newsitem>
        <newsheader date="November 3rd"><link ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX V3.82</link>
          available and fresh <dblink id="turntables">turntables</dblink></newsheader>
        <newstext>
          <para><img filename="webknob.jpg" align="right"/>
			Some fresh code finally! Here's what's new with this release:

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>Support for <bold>stereo LADSPA plugins</bold>. Each
			  		turntable now features a stereo effect queue that follows the 
					mono queue. Click the "Stereo FX" button to add stereo plugins
					to a turntable's effect queue.
                </para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Every plugin can now have an extra <bold>Dry/Wet control</bold>
			  		if required. Click on a plugin's label to add or remove
					the control.
				</para></listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>You can now map <bold>MIDI controllers reverse</bold>: this introduces
						the possibilty to map a MIDI controller as a crossfader for two (or more)
						turntables.
					</para>
				</listitem>
              <listitem><para>
			  	<person><name>Adam King</name><email>aking@lgh.com.au</email></person> contributed
				a patch that adds <bold>simpler minimization</bold> for control panels and a fix for 
				a sequencer menu crash.
                </para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>
				This release supports the gtk+ <bold>filechooser</bold> where available.
                </para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>All VU meters now display the <bold>stereo signal</bold>.
                </para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>For security reasons the old suid-root method has <bold>gone</bold> - the
				POSIX capabilties-based method remains available as it's currently believed to
				be secure.
                </para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>
				From the unnecessary-eye-candy dept.: this release
			  		features <bold>new icons</bold> I've drawn with the cool 
					<link ref="http://www.inkscape.org">inkscape</link>	and a <bold>new
					control knob</bold> I've created with the wonderful 
					<link ref="http://www.povray.org">povray</link>. And of course
					I've used the <link ref="http://www.gimp.org">Gimp</link> all over
					the place. All images should now blend smoothly with your
					theme's background.
                </para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		  </para>
		  <para>
			For more details check the <dblink id="changelog"/>. As usual I've verified this release 
			to build with all gcc releases from 2.95 to 3.4, it fixes a
			a whole lot of bugs and it's available from the <dblink id="download"/>.
		  </para>
		  <para>
			Additionally I finally managed to add two new turntables to the 
			<dblink id="turntables"/>. <person>
            <name>Bob's</name>
            <email>curious@pb194.luban.sdi.tpnet.pl</email>
          </person> turntable is based on a new belt-driven approach while
		  <person>
            <name>Adam's</name>
            <email>aking@lgh.com.au</email>
          </person> turntable is interesting from the inside as well as the
		  outside.
		  </para>
		</newstext>
	  </newsitem>
      <newsitem>
        <newsheader date="August 22"><link ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX V3.81</link>
          available</newsheader>
        <newstext>
          <para>The new release introduces the following features:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>I've added a <bold>new audio back-end</bold> for the 
                  <dblink id="jack">JACK Audio Connection Kit</dblink>. To make use of it
                  the JACK Daemon has to run <italic>before</italic> starting terminatorX.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                  <bold>Note:</bold> JACK seems to lockup when clients run with realtime
                  scheduling (SCHED_FIFO) - terminatorX can work around this when running
                  with capabilities, but not with the old <screen>--enable-suidroot</screen>
                  mode - so don't enable it when you want to use the JACK back-end. Reniceing
                  via libjack works fine btw (see this
                  <link ref="http://jackit.sourceforge.net/docs/faq.php#a5">JACK FAQ entry</link>).
                </para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>A new <bold>Parameter Menu</bold>: simply right-click on the 
                parameter of your choice and set the MIDI mappings, bounds or delete events.
              </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <screenshot filename="parameter_menu.jpg"><nopara>Parameter Menu</nopara></screenshot>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>The new <bold>MIDI Bounds</bold> let you modify the range
                  within which a MIDI controller can effect a certain parameter.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>The new <bold>MIDI Learn</bold> mode provides a much simpler
                  method of mapping MIDI events than the "regular" MIDI mappings dialog.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem><para>terminatorX now tries to <bold>reconnect to previously connected MIDI 
                  devices</bold> on startup. Might only work with hardware devices (and can
                  therefor be disabled).</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>I finally got sick of green: you can now <bold>adjust the
                colors</bold> of terminatorX' own widgets (audio signal display and 
                vu meters).
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>You can now <bold>erase events from the sequencer</bold> for 
                  either a complete turntable or a specific parameter for either
                  the complete song or from or upto the current song position.
                </para>                
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  There's a new <bold>Confirm Recorded Events</bold> mode that allows
                  you to discard a take if you're not satisfied with it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Support for <bold>Linux' POSIX capabilities</bold> implementation
                  brings a new, <italic>possibly safer</italic> way of running terminatorX 
                  suid-root to achieve realtime scheduling (see the yet again updated 
                  <link ref="faq.html#11">FAQ entry</link>).
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>There's a new <bold>Default MIDI Mapping</bold> for the standard
                  parameters, so you don't have to create too many mappings yourself (if the
                  default map suits your needs of course). The defaults are documented
                  in the terminatorX manual.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>            
          </para>
          <para>
            Additonally this release fixes a lot of bugs:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Fixed the problems that where found with the old suid-root approach.
                  However there could be other ways to exploit this, so I recommend
                  using the new capabilities based approach instead - if you really want to run 
                  terminatorX suid-root. If you want to use the old approach you'll 
                  have to run configure with <screen>--enable-suidroot</screen>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>compiles with gcc flavours from 2.95 to 3.3.1 (tested)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>setting <italic>Sync Client</italic> via MIDI now works
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>lots of code cleanups, now compiles with 
                <screen>G*_DISABLE_DEPRECATED</screen> macros enabled.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>fixed restoring of master volume setting
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>introduced a workaround for 
                  <link ref="http://www-stud.fht-esslingen.de/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=4">Bug #4</link>, so
                  if the ALSA back-end segfaults for you, check you have "Free HW Stats"
                  disabled.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>corrected clearing of events for the master parameters
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>fixed a FreeBSD issue with the configure script.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <para>OK, I hope this release works for you, if you want to check it out
              grab it from the <dblink id="download"/>.
          </para>
        </newstext>
      </newsitem>
      <newsitem>
        <newsheader date="August 05">Updates, 3.81 on the way</newsheader>
        <newstext>
          <para>As shown in this <link ref="http://www.securityfocus.com/archive/1/328469">bugtraq
            post</link> by <person>
              <name>Andrew Griffiths</name>
              <email>andrewg@felinemenace.org</email>
            </person> installing terminatorX suid root is <bold>exploitable</bold>. Although you had been
            warned before, I decided to change my <link ref="faq.html#11">recommendation</link>.
            To make bug tracking easier in the future I've setup a 
            <dblink id="bugs">bugzilla</dblink> for terminatorX.</para>
          <para>Additionally the website now features a new <dblink id="links"/>.</para>
          <para>
            <person>
              <name>Arthur Moore</name>
              <email>art@infinitybox.net</email>
            </person> is a &quot;twentieth-century&quot; composer who is using terminatorX for his 
            compositions. I've
            added three of his compositions to the <dblink id="scratches"/> to find out more about
            the author and his music check out his <link ref="http://infinitybox.net">site</link>.</para>
          <para>The kind people of <dblink id="sonar"/> invited me to do a demonstration at this
            year's festival. As a side effect I was actually forced to <bold>use</bold> terminatorX,
            so I found and fixed quite some annoying bugs with the upcoming 3.81 release.
            Additionally it will feature MIDI and sequencer improvements and a <dblink id="jack"/> 
            back-end.</para>
        </newstext>
      </newsitem>
      <newsitem>
        <newsheader date="April 18">
          <link ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX 3.80</link> and <link
            ref="aseqjoy.html">aseqjoy 0.0.1</link>
        </newsheader>
        <newstext>
          <para>This terminatorX release does a very good job at extinguishing points from my
            TODO-for-4.0 list. Among other things this release introduces: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Finally terminatorX has a <bold>native</bold>
                  <dblink id="alsa"/>
                  <bold>back-end</bold>. See the new <italic>Preferences</italic> dialog and the
                  online manual for details. The ALSA and the OSS back-ends now both support
                  operating at an <bold>arbitrary sampling rate</bold>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <screenshot filename="shot-3.80-1.png">
              <nopara>Scrolling audio data, a menu bar and even less space consumption for small
                displays. </nopara>
            </screenshot>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The audio data display is now <bold>zoomable</bold>. This helps scratching
                  large audio files (like complete songs) significantly. Use the slider on the right
                  of the display area to adjust the zoom level. When playing the audio data will
                  scroll in such a manner that the current position is always centered.</para>
                <para>To optimize playback performance terminatorX does a lot of
                  &quot;zoom&quot; calculations in advance - so adjusting the slider will
                  cause quite some amount of recalculation on large audio files. The focused
                  turntable now has a blue background and a yellow audio signal instead of the old
                  red border.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>A <bold>MIDI interface</bold> thanks to a patch by <person>
                    <name>Arthur Peters</name>
                    <email>amp@singingwizard.org</email>
                  </person>. The MIDI interface is based upon the <dblink id="alsa"/> sequencer API,
                  so you'll have to connect terminatorX' input port to an output port of your choice
                  with either <screen>aconnect</screen> or for example the <link
                    ref="http://pkl.net/~node/alsa-patch-bay.html"> alsa-patch-bay</link>. To map a
                  MIDI controller or note events to a turntable's parameter click the <italic>MIDI
                  Mapping</italic> button.</para>
                <para>In order to test the new interface I hacked a little tool called <dblink
                  id="aseqjoy"/> that emits MIDI controller messages based on Joystick motion.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>I finally untied audio rendering and audio back-end. terminatorX now operates
                  at a <bold>fixed internal block size</bold> of 1 ms. So now it doesn't matter
                  anymore with which block size events were recorded - they will be played back
                  correctly with any audio device block size.</para>
                <para>Note that a minor problem remains: the sampling rate has an effect on the
                  block size, too. While there is no problem switching from 22 or 32 kHz to 48 kHz,
                  there will be a slight rounding error switching from or to 44.1 kHz. So if you
                  record and playback events I suggest you keep the sampling rate the same, or use
                  &quot;straight&quot; sampling rates like 22, 32 and 48 kHz only.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>I added a little <bold>pitch calculator</bold> that allows adjusting the
                  playback speed of a turntable to that of the master turntable so it is very easy
                  to synchronize (<italic>precisely cut</italic>) loops now. Note that this feature
                  is probably useless with large audio files (like complete songs).</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Advancing the use of XML: many XML-related bugs have been fixed, and I moved
                  the <bold>set file format to XML</bold>, too. The MIDI mappings of parameters will
                  be stored within set files, too. As XML set files with a lot of sequencer events
                  can grow quite big tX supports writing <bold>gzip compressed set files</bold>
                  through the use of <link ref="http://www.zlib.org">zlib</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Thanks to a suggestion by <person>
                    <name>Darrick Servis</name>
                    <email>darrick@dcn.davis.ca.us</email>
                  </person> terminatorX <bold>no longer clips audio</bold>. If the generated
                  amplitude goes beyond the maximum it will simply be cut off.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Further cleaning up the layout for small DJ laptop displays: moved some
                  buttons to a <bold>menu bar</bold> to waste less space. Additionally you can now
                  hit <screen>F11</screen> to enter <bold>full screen</bold> mode - if your window
                  manager supports <italic>NETWM</italic>.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Dropped support for the old gtk+ 1.2 - you have to use gtk+ &gt;= 2.0, now.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <para>This release has seen quite some <link
            ref="http://developer.kde.org/~sewardj">valgrinding</link> so it should run rather
            stable and a major memory leak has been fixed, too. Unlike 3.73 this one compiles with gcc
            &gt; 3.0 with <screen>-Wall</screen> and <screen>-Werror</screen> enabled. Well, the
            version number ends in a zero, which means lots of new code with possibly lots of new
            and yet undiscovered bugs. </para>
        </newstext>
      </newsitem>
      <newsitem>
        <newsheader date="18 Sep">
          <link ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX V3.73</link> available, <link
          ref="http://www.debian.org">Debian</link> inclusion + a <dblink id="tutorial"/>
        </newsheader>
        <newstext>
          <para>Aside of fixing numerous bugs, the new release does have some new features: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>I ported terminatorX to <link ref="http://www.gtk.org">gtk+</link>
                  <bold>Version 2</bold> so tX should integrate nicely with your GNOME 2 desktop.
                  This release still builds with the old gtk+ 1.2, too, but I don't plan to support
                  it much longer.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>I reworked the GUI a bit in order to make terminatorX fit better on those
                  small DJ-laptop displays. Audio and control panels can now be minimized to a
                    <bold>panel bar</bold> to save space - works just like GNOME's window list. The
                  panel bar status is stored within set files and restored upon loading. Additionally
                  the buttons of the audio panel have been restructured. To lighten up the GUI five
                  buttons have been merged into <bold>two</bold> - on clicking one of these you'll
                  get a popup menu with all previous functionality.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>After spending an evening with Adrian in front of his big endian system fixing
                  the audio file loading routines, I decided that loading audio files through a pipe
                  is an ugly hack. Therefor I wrote <bold>three new audio file loading
                  methods</bold> that utilize libraries instead of pipes. These are <link
                    ref="http://www.mars.org/home/rob/proj/mpeg/"> mad</link> (for mp3 files), <link
                  ref="http://www.xiph.org/ogg/vorbis/">libvorbis</link> (for OGG/Vorbis files) and
                    <link ref="http://www.68k.org/~michael/audiofile/"> libaudiofile</link> (for
                  wav/aiff/au etc.). Using these routines instead of the old ones brings the
                  following advantages: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>loading audio files is significantly <bold>faster</bold>
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>terminatorX now evaluates the <bold>sample rate</bold> of an audio file
                        and adjusts the turntable's pitch accordingly (this does not affect the
                        regular &quot;pitch&quot; setting BTW)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>the new routines provide much better <bold>visual feedback</bold> on the
                        loading progress</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>Additionally more file formats are supported, so I strongly
                  recommend installing the libraries mentioned above to improve terminatorX' usability.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Slowly approaching terminator <bold>XML</bold>: the configuration file (now
                  <italic>~/.terminatorXrc</italic>) is no longer binary but an XML document. This
                  is necessary to become more flexible in the future - and it allows editing your
                  terminatorX configuration with a text editor - if you want to. Of course,
                  terminatorX now requires <link ref="http://www.libxml.org">libxml</link> to be
                  installed. For convenience this release still reads the old binary con figuration and
                  stores it as an XML document on exit. I plan to move the set file format to XML
                  soon, too.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>I completely rewrote the <italic>tX_engine</italic> in order to allow
                  installing terminatorX <bold>suid root</bold>. This way terminatorX can run with
                  realtime scheduling policy even for unprivileged users. Right after creation of
                  the engine thread terminatorX drops root privileges - so it might even be safe to
                  install terminatorX suid root - but I'll leave that up to security experts to
                  decide. For a more detailed discussion read <link ref="faq.html#11">this FAQ entry</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Playing around with the wonderful <link
                  ref="http://www.povray.org">povray</link> a bit I came up with a new logo for
                  terminatorX. The icons have been replaced, too - the new ones should be easier for
                  your desktop perception.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Thanks to <person>
                    <name>Adrian</name>
                    <email>adrian@lisas.de</email>
                  </person> terminatorX now has a <bold>manpage</bold>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <para>A lot of bug fixing went into this release, too, most notably: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>An old clipping bug in the <italic>tX_dial</italic> widget code has been fixed.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>This release builds, runs and loads audio files on big endian architectures.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>terminatorX should now build from scratch not only on Linux but on FreeBSD,
                  too. Thanks to <person>
                    <name>Tilman Linneweh</name>
                    <email>tilman@arved.de</email>
                  </person> for testing.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Many other fixes.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>Have a look at the <dblink id="changelog"/> for more
            details and grab the tarball or the RPMs from the <link
              ref="download.html#Current Version">download section</link>.</para>
          <para>Aside of the release I'd like to bring to your attention that <person>
              <name>Mike Furr</name>
              <email>mfurr@debian.org</email>
            </person> is now maintainer of the <link
              ref="http://packages.debian.org/unstable/sound/terminatorx.html"> terminatorX Debian
            package</link>. So if you're a Debian user you may want to <italic>apt-get</italic> this
            release - if you install <italic>unstable</italic> packages at all and when your local
            mirror has been updated.</para>
          <para>For new terminatorX users <person>
              <name>Brian</name>
              <email>bredfern@calarts.edu</email>
            </person> has created a wonderful step-by-step <dblink id="tutorial">
              &quot;terminatorX TOOT&quot; tutorial</dblink> - reading that will accelerate
            the creation of your first scratch considerably.</para>
        </newstext>
      </newsitem>
      <!--<newsitem>
        <newsheader date="31 Jul">
          <dblink id="turntables">Turntable gallery</dblink> online and a fresh <dblink id="scratches">scratch</dblink>
        </newsheader>
        <newstext>
          <para>I finally managed to hack the website's DTD and XSLT stylesheet to support the <link
              ref="turntable.html">users' turntable section</link>. Now that it's easy to update,
            please keep these turntable images coming in! I'd really like to see more of your turntables.</para>
          <para>
            <person>
              <name>Brian</name>
              <email>bredfern@calarts.edu</email>
            </person> - a California based terminatorX DJ - has contributed a very cool scratch for
            the <dblink id="scratches">scratches section</dblink>. It's just an excerpt of a
            complete drum and bass set that is available at Brian's <link
            ref="http://asapien.org">website</link> - which seems to be down currently. In case it
            doesn't come up again I'll mirror the complete set here, too.</para>
          <para>
            <italic>The names have been changed to protect the innocent...</italic> from
            <bold>spamming</bold>. The XSLT stylesheet now mangles all email addresses on this site
            except for mine - if you've seen a correct email address before you should be able to
            recover the real address easily. BTW if you're a spam victim, too, add the incredible
              <link ref="http://spamassassin.org">spamassassin</link> to your
            <italic>.procmailrc</italic> and spam won't annoy you anymore.</para>
          <para>On terminatorX news Version 3.73 should be ready for release RSN! It will probably
            still lack native ALSA support, though.</para>
        </newstext>
      </newsitem>
      <newsitem>
        <newsheader date="05 jan">happy new year: <link
            ref="download.html#Current Version">terminatorX V3.72</link> is here.</newsheader>
        <newstext>
          <para>Hope everybody had a nice start into 2002, these are the changes that come with
            terminatorX release 3.72 (for details check the <dblink id="changelog"/>): <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Thanks to a patch from <person>
                    <name>Matthew Evans</name>
                    <email>activesx@hotmail.com</email>
                  </person>terminatorX finally supports loading <link
                    ref="http://www.vorbis.com">Ogg Vorbis</link> audio files. Note that this feature
                  requires ogg123 (&gt;= RC2) and <link
                  ref="http://sox.sourceforge.net">sox</link> installed. The very fresh RC3 release
                  of Ogg Vorbis works just fine, too.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <person>
                    <name>Adrian</name>
                    <email>adrian@lisas.de</email>
                  </person>once again submitted code to the project: terminatorX now features
                  <bold>mute</bold> and <bold>solo</bold> buttons for each turntable's mixing unit.
                  The initial patch had some problems with the already existing mute-function in
                  terminatorX, therefor I extended the turntable in such a way that the new buttons
                    <bold>only affect current mixing</bold> - the sequencer will not record any
                  events for them.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>I updated the XInput code to work with XFree86 &gt; 4. terminatorX now
                  uses the <italic>xsetpointer</italic> binary that comes with XFree86 to switch the
                  core pointer - as the old code doesn't work with newer XFree86 releases anymore.
                  <italic>configure</italic> should auto-detect <italic>xsetpointer</italic> if it's
                  available. <bold>Note:</bold> You only need to specify an additional XInput Device
                  in the options dialog if you want to use a scratching device other than your
                  mouse. (Yeah, I know, I state that in the docs, tooltips, everywhere - but I still
                  get bug reports related to that issue...)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Updated mpg123 loading routines that should work with <link
                  ref="http://mpg321.sourceforge.net">mpg321</link> (which many distros install
                  instead of mpg123 these days), too. Note that you'll have to have <link
                  ref="http://sox.sourceforge.net">sox</link> installed in order to get mp3-loading
                  to work (As mpg321 doesn't support mpg123's <italic>-m</italic> switch).</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>fixes for misc bugs (writing broken .wav's on big endian machines, gcc
                  &gt;= 3.x compile fixes, some gtk+ cleanups, etc.)</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <para>Grab the sources or the fresh RPMs (Thanks, <person>
              <name>Adrian</name>
              <email>adrian@lisas.de</email>
            </person>!) from the <link ref="download.html#Current Version">download section</link>.</para>
          <para>Initially I planned to integrate native <link
            ref="http://www.alsa-project.org">ALSA</link>-support into this release but I simply
            failed to finish. As many people wanted to have some of the above features early I
            decided to release it without ALSA now, as I'll be busy for the upcoming weeks. I
            haven't given up on ALSA though, hopefully the next terminatorX release will feature a
            new audio device back-end that supports ALSA (V0.9) <bold>and</bold> OSS and brings many
            other advantages.</para>
          <para>The website has undergone minor updates, too: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The section header's now should look fine with <link
                  ref="http://www.mozilla.org">Mozilla</link>-based browsers. They might look funny
                  with older Netscape releases, though.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Updated the <link ref="screenshots.html">screenshots</link> as people started
                  asking howto achieve that old tX V3.5 layout :)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Minor fixes to make <link ref="http://www.w3.org">W3C</link>'s validator
                  accept the pages again, and a favicon that needs some improvement.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </newstext>
      </newsitem>-->
    </news>
  </main>
</section>
