<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY GFDL SYSTEM "fdl-appendix.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "0.3.5">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "0.1.1">
  <!ENTITY date "March 18, 2002">
  <!-- Information about the entities
       The legal.xml file contains legal information, there is no need to edit the file.
       Use the appversion entity to specify the version of the application.
       Use the manrevision entity to specify the revision number of this manual.
       Use the date entity to specify the release date of this manual.
       Use the app entity to specify the name of the application. -->
]>
<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>terminatorX - Manual</title>
    <author><firstname>Alexander</firstname>
      <surname>K&ouml;nig</surname></author>
    <copyright><year>1999 - 2002</year>
      <holder ROLE="mailto:alex@rhlx01.fht-esslingen.de">Alexander K&ouml;nig</holder></copyright>
    <releaseinfo>Version 3.73</releaseinfo></articleinfo>
  <preface id="preface">
    <title>Preface</title>
    <para>This is free software see the
      <filename moreinfo="NONE">COPYING</filename>
      file that came with this distribution for details.</para>
    <para><emphasis>Warning:</emphasis> TerminatorX comes with
      <emphasis>ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY</emphasis>. This software is
      known o lockup X11 or cause other problems under rare conditions. Don't
      use it on production servers. You have been
      warned!</para></preface>

  <section id="INTRODUCTION"><title>Introduction</title>
    <section id="WHATITIS"><title>What it is</title>
      <para><application moreinfo="NONE">terminatorX</application> is a
	realtime audio synthesizer that allows you to "scratch" on
	digitally sampled audio data (*.wav, *.au, *.mp3, *.ogg etc.)
	the way hiphop-DJs scratch on vinyl records. It features
	multiple turntables, realtime effects (built-in as well as
	LADSPA plugin effects), a sequencer and an easy-to-use gtk+
	GUI.</para>

      <para>This is <emphasis>beta</emphasis> Software please help me
	fix bugs. See <xref linkend="CONTACT"/>
	(Contact/Download). Please read this manual and take a look at
	the
	<ulink url="http://www.terminatorX.cx">homepage</ulink>.
      </para></section>

    <section id="QUICKSTART"><title>Quickstart</title>
      <orderedlist CONTINUATION="RESTARTS"
		   INHERITNUM="IGNORE"><listitem><para>If you don't have
	    <application moreinfo="NONE">LADSPA</application> (Linux
	    Audio Developer's Simple Plugin API) installed, go and get
	    it from the 
	    <ulink url="http://www.ladspa.org">LADSPA-homepage</ulink>
	    and install the SDK. terminatorX requires 
	    <filename moreinfo="NONE">ladspa.h</filename>.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Install terminatorX (see 
	    <filename moreinfo="NONE">INSTALL</filename>)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Run terminatorX</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Load an audiofile into the available turntable
	    (you can add more turntables if you want) (Hint: Click on
	    the button that holds "NONE" to load an audiofile, or drop
	    one over the audiofile display from your filemanager if your
	    filemanager is efm, gmc, Nautilus or compatible (kfm does
	    <emphasis>not</emphasis> work))</para></listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Load a LADSPA plugin of your choice by clicking the
	    turntable's <emphasis>FX</emphasis> button and enable it.
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem><para>Click on the "Audio Engine"-button to start
	    playback.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Click on the "Mouse-Grab"-button to enter grab
	    mode. The turntable with the red border has the input
	    focus.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Press <keycap moreinfo="NONE">SPACE</keycap> or
	    left mouse button to scratch.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Release <keycap moreinfo="NONE">SPACE</keycap>  or left mouse button to let the scratch-file run at the turntable's default speed.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Press <keycap moreinfo="NONE">ESCAPE</keycap> to
	    quit grab mode.</para></listitem></orderedlist></section>

    <section id="FEATURES"><title>Features</title>
      <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Scratching ;)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Multiple turntables</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Built-in Sequencer</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Pitch / Volume settings for each turntable</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Effects (Lowpass/Echo) configurable for each turntable</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Syncing tables to one master turntable</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Broad audiofile-type support through the use of sox and mpg123</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Recording (straight to disk now)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Save turntable sets (.tX - files)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Support for the LADSPA-plugin-standard.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>and more</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section>
    <section id="REQUIREMENTS"><title>Requirements</title>
      <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Software</para>
	  <itemizedlist><listitem><para>required</para>
	      <itemizedlist><listitem><para>The Linux Operating System (Version &gt;=
		    2.0) or FreeBSD</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>glibc2 (pthreads).</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>XFree86 (with DGA DirectMouse
		    support). Note that XFree86 Release 4.0 has a bug
		    resulting in broken DirectMouse support. This has
		    been fixed by the XFree86-Team with Release 4.0.1
		    available from your distribution or the 
		    <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org">XFree86
		      homepage</ulink>.
		  </para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>The Gimp Toolkit: gtk+ (>= 1.2.5) - Version 2 of gtk+ is
		    supported, too. If your distribution doesn't provide
		    a current version of gtk+ get it from the 
		    <ulink url="http://www.gtk.org">gtk+
		      homepage</ulink>.
		  </para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>LADSPA - the Linux Audio Developer's
		    Simple Plugin API. Get it from the
		    <ulink url="http://www.ladpsa.org">LADSPA homepage</ulink>
		  </para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>a compiler
		    (gcc)</para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>optional</para>
	      <itemizedlist><listitem><para>
		    <ulink url="http://home.sprynet.com/~cbagwell/sox.html">sox</ulink>
		    for enhanced audio file support</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <ulink url="http://www-ti.informatik.uni-tuebingen.de/~hippm/mpg123.html">mpg123</ulink>
		    for mp3 support</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <ulink url="http://www.xiph.org/ogg/vorbis/">ogg123</ulink>
		    for Ogg Vorbis support</para></listitem>

	      </itemizedlist></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Hardware</para>
	  <itemizedlist><listitem><para>An OSS compatible soundcard
		capable of stereo output. This includes
		<emphasis>all</emphasis> 
		<ulink url="http://www.alsa-project.org">ALSA-driven</ulink> 
		soundcards as this enhanced audio device interface includes support for
		the OSS API.</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para>A good clean mouse and pad, a good X-Pointer
		setup.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem></itemizedlist>

      <para>A note on performance: terminatorX is known to run
	satisfyingly on pentium-class systems (or above of
	course). Increasing the number of turntables or plugins will of
	course require more performant systems.</para></section>

    <section id="INSTALLATION"><title>Installation</title>
      <para>For GNU-standards' sake this information is now located in
	the <filename moreinfo="NONE">INSTALL</filename> file that came
	with this distribution of
	terminatorX.</para></section></section>

  <section id="OPERATION"><title>Operation</title>
    <para>With Release Version 3.70 the terminatorX has undergone some
      redesign again. It's split up in the main controls (master,
      sequencer, engine controls and menu buttons) and the individual
      turntable's controls. Each turntable has it's own GUI split up
      into control and audio panel.</para>

    <section id="MAINCONTROLS"><title>Main Controls</title>
      <para>The controls of the master gui are located in the top and
	the right bar of the terminatorX main window.</para>
      <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Audio Engine Power / Mouse
	      Grab</emphasis></para>

	  <para>With the Audio Engine Button you can en- and disable the
	    audio playback engine without activating the
	    sequencer. Unlike earlier versions you will not
	    automatically enter mouse-grab mode so you can modify
	    volume/pitch/echo settings etc. while you actually hear what
	    you do. </para>

	  <para>Some functions are not available when the audio engine is on, their controls will be marked insensitive when you enable the engine. To actually enter grab mode you'll have to click on the "Mouse Grab" button. See <xref linkend="GRABMODE"/> (Grab Mode Operation) to find out how to control the software then.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><emphasis>Record (Audio
	      Engine)</emphasis></para>

	  <para>To enable recording you have to enable the "Record"-toggle button BEFORE you 
	    start the audio engine. You will be prompted for a filename after enabling the
	    button. Audio will then be recorded to that file in stereo
	    RIFF/WAV format from the moment you turn the audio engine on
	    until you turn it off again. Please be aware of the fact
	    that recording audio requires <emphasis>a lot</emphasis> of
	    harddisk space!</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis>Sequencer Play / Record / Stop</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Please read the Sequencer-Section to find out more about
	    the sequencer.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis>Master Volume /
	      Pitch</emphasis></para>

	  <para>The volume and pitch settings of the individual
	    turntables are relative to these master settings. This
	    information will be stored within the .tX set
	    files.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis>Add Turntable</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Oh well, it says it all: adds a (new) turntable to the
	    current set.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis>Save Set</emphasis></para>
	  <para>With this button you can save your current set and all related settings to a 
	    .tX set file. Note that the audiofiles themselves will not be stored within
	    these files but only references to them. Therefore on loading the set the 
	    audiofiles have to be at the same location in the filesystem as they were when
	    putting that set together.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><emphasis>Load Set</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Loads a previously saved set (see above). The current
	    set will be destroyed!</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis>Options</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Displays the options dialog. See
	    <xref linkend="CONFIGURATION"/>
	    (Options/Configuration).</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem><para><emphasis>About/Legal</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Displays a dialog with some info about the prog and the
	    binary itself plus the good old GPL.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis>Quit</emphasis></para>
	  <para>No comment.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section>
    <section id="TURNtableCONTROLS"><title>Turntable Controls</title>
      <para>The turntable GUI contains multiple controls and the
	realtime displays for each turntable. To save some space on your
	desktop and to give terminatorX the traditional
	audio-application look, terminatorX features
	&quot;knob&quot;-widgets. These widgets work pretty
	straight-forward: click somewhere within the widget and keep the
	left mouse-button pressed. Now move the mouse up and down or
	left and right to increase/decrease the control's value. All
	those widget are coupled with a text entry field since 3.70,
	which allows you to enter values directly.</para>

      <para>A turntable is visualized by two panels: the control and the
	audio panel. These are no longer combined for better layout
	management.</para>
      <para>
	Sometimes you might find a certain audio or control panel
	unnecessary - simply eating up space. Since release 3.73 it is
	possible to minimize audio and control panels to the 
	<emphasis>panel bar</emphasis> with the tiny button with a blue
	bar icon in the upper right edge of each panel. This bar works
	just like GNOME's
	window list or KDE's kicker: When a panel is minimized a button in
	the bar will appear, representing the minimized window. On
	clicking this button the button will be removed and the
	minimized panel is displayed again. When no panels are minimized
	the panel bar automatically disappears to save display space.
</para>
      <section><title>Turntable Audio Panel</title>
	<para>The complete audio-file loaded into a turntable is
	  displayed in the green-on-black audio-widget. When playing
	  terminatorX will indicate the current position within the
	  sample with a red cursor (a blue/green cursor indicates the
	  turntable is muted).</para>

	<para>Additionaly there are some controls above the audio-display:</para>
	<itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Turntable Label</emphasis></para>
	    <para>This label indicates the turntables name. The name can
	      be set via the control panel</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis>File Button</emphasis></para>
	    <para>This button holds the name of the audio-file currently
	      loaded. When there's no sample loaded the button will read
	      &quot;NONE&quot; to indicate the current status. 
	      Click on this button to get a menu from which you can
	      load/reload a sound file or run an external soundfile
	      editor. Alternatively you can drag'n'drop
	      files over the audio-display to load
	      them.</para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <title>The File Button Menu</title>
	      <listitem><para><emphasis>Load File</emphasis></para>
		<para>Choose this menu entry to select a soundfile from
		  the file-selection dialog that will pop-up.
		</para></listitem>

	      <listitem><para><emphasis>Reload File</emphasis></para>
		<para>Choose this menu entry to re-read the
		  audio-file.</para></listitem>

	      <listitem><para><emphasis>Edit File</emphasis></para>
		<para>This menu entry will run the external audiofile-editor
		  (that can be specified via the options-dialog) with
		  the current audio-file as a parameter. Choose
		  reload after editing and saving the
		  file.</para></listitem>

	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Mouse Mapping</emphasis></para>
	    <para>terminatorX allows mapping misc parameters to the
	      mouse axis of your choice. These mappings will be
	      activated in grab mode, so if you move your mouse in X or
	      Y direction in grab mode the parameters you selected from
	      this menu will be affected (for this turntable). Since
	      Version 3.70 this mappings are no longer hardcoded to
	      built-in controls but available for all parameters that
	      qualify as &quot;mappable&quot;. Note that this includes
	      plugins' controls as
	      well.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section>

      <section><title>Turntable Controls</title>
	<para>These controls are now grouped within functional
	  panels. The number of panels depends on the number of plugins
	  loaded. terminatorX allows hiding the controls not required
	  via the yellow triangle button. To un-hide just click the
	  button again. The first panels are the standard controls for a
	  turntable, then follows the dynamic FX-section and below that
	  follow the pitch and volume controls.</para>
	
	<section><title>Main Panel</title>
	  <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Name Field</emphasis></para>
	      <para>The main panel features a text entry field that
		allows setting a name for the related turntable. The
		Labels for the controls and the audio-display will
		update accordingly.</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Delete Button</emphasis></para>
	      <para>Pressing this button remove the tunrtable from the
		current setup. Note that all sequencer events recorded
		for this turntable will be erased,
		too.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section>

	<section><title>Trigger Panel</title>
	  <para>The trigger panel holds all controls related to
	    triggering the turntable. For more details on
	    synchronization see <xref linkend="SYNCHRONIZATION"/>
	    (synchronization).</para>

	  <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Trigger! Button</emphasis></para>
	      <para>Pressing this button triggers the turntable
		now. With the audio engine enabled this will cause the
		turntable to start playing back audio from the beginning
		of the sample.</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Stop Button</emphasis></para>
	      <para>Guess what, this stops this turntable's
		audio-playback.</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Master Button</emphasis></para>
	      <para>Enabling this button makes this turntable the
		<emphasis>sync-master</emphasis>. Note that only
		<emphasis>one</emphasis> turntable at a time can be the
		sync-master.</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Client Button</emphasis></para>
	      <para>This button marks the turntable as
		<emphasis>sync-client</emphasis>, so it will be triggerd
		with the master automatically.</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Sync-Cycles Selection</emphasis></para>
	      <para>The sync cycles determine how often a sync-client
		should be triggered. With a setting of zero the
		sync-client will be (re-)triggered with
		<emphasis>every</emphasis> trigger of the sync-master. A
		setting of 1 will (re-)trigger the client every
		<emphasis>second</emphasis> master-triger and so
		on.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>

	  <para>Below the effect queue a turntable shows some more controls:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis>Pitch Control</emphasis></para>
		<para>The pitch control allows setting the default playback
		  speed for that turntable (the "motor" speed). Negative values
		  will result in the sample being played backwards.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis>PAN Control</emphasis></para>
		<para>This parameter allows setting the position of the
		  turntable's main signal within the stereo panorama.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis>VU Meter</emphasis></para>
		<para>The displayed signal shows the turntable's current
		  signal not including the echo-signal which is mixed
		  separately.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>

	  </para>

	</section></section>
      <section><title>The Effect Queue</title>
	<para>With release 3.70 the effects are no longer hardcoded into
	  the turntable. The effects are now arranged within an
	  per-turntable effect-queue. The effect sequence is
	  configurable by the user. To move an effect to higher position
	  within the queue, press the <emphasis>blue upward arrow
	    button</emphasis>. This will cause the effect to be renderd
	  <emphasis>before</emphasis> the following effects. The
	  <emphasis>blue downward arrow button</emphasis> will move the
	  effect down by one position. It will then be rendered
	  <emphasis>after</emphasis> the preceding effects.</para>


	<para>There are two types of effects: the traditional built-in
	  effects (Lowpass and Echo) and LADSPA plugins. The built-in
	  effects are always available and cannot be removed (but
	  disabled). There can be only one instance of a built-in
	  effect. The LADSPA plugins on the other hand may be
	  instanciated multiple times and can be removed from the effect
	  queue. Press the <emphasis>blue cross button</emphasis> to
	  achieve this.</para>

	<figure float="0">
	  <title>An example for a terminatorX effect queue</title>
	  <graphic fileref="figures/signalflow" scale="27"/>
	</figure>
	<para>Now since release 3.71 the built-in echo effect is treated
	  differently from other effects. Where all other effects feed
	  their signal back into the effect queue the echo effect
	  doesn't touch the input signal. It's echo-signal is mixed
	  seperately from the turntable's main signal to allow a
	  different panning value for the echo-signal. This mode of
	  operation does have some side-effects: imagine a lowpass
	  filter with a position after the echo effect in the effect
	  queue. This will result in the turntable's main signal being
	  lowpassed but it will leave the echo-signal
	  un-lowpassed.</para>

	<para>Some may call this behaviour a bug - whereas I would
	  consider it a feature ;). Anyway if the above description
	  didn't clear things up maybe the displayed figure does. It
	  shows a schematic effect queue with the built-in effects and
	  two LADSPA effects enabled. Now with this setup you will not
	  hear anything from the second LADSPA effect in the
	  echo-signal.</para>


	<para>For more information on a LADSPA plugin, press it's panel's label and a small info box will pop up.</para>
	<itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>FX Button</emphasis></para>
	    <para>Press this button to load a LADSPA plugin into the
	      effect queue of the turntable. A menu holding the
	      available (terminatorX-&quot;compatible&quot;)
	      LADSPA-plugins will pop up. The plugins are grouped within
	      submenus according to the modules the plugins are
	      contained in. Simply select the plugin you want to load
	      from this menu and a panel for it will pop up at the end
	      of the effect queue.</para>

	    <para>Note that due to the wide parameter ranges some LADSPA
	      plugins have they sometimes might be hard to control with
	      the knob widget. In these cases you might want to use the
	      text field to enter values. For more details on Plugins
	      see <xref linkend="LADSPAPLUGINS"/>
	      (LASDPA).</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section>

      <section><title>Lowpass Panel</title>
	<para>terminatorX features a builtin resonating lowpass filter
	  that can be configured with this panel.</para>

	<itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Enable Button</emphasis></para>
	    <para>Activating this button will enable the lowpass filter
	      for this turntable.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis>Input Gain Control</emphasis></para>
	    <para>With this parameter you can amplify the signal that
	      goes into the lowpass filter if
	      required.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis>Frequency Control</emphasis></para>
	    <para>Use this parameter to set the cutoff frequency for the
	      lowpass filter. Minimum: 0=0Hz, Maximum:
	      1=22KHz.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis>Resonance</emphasis></para>
	    <para>Use this parameter to set the
	      resonance-value. Minimum: 0=no resonance, Maximum: 1=max
	      resonance.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section>

      <section><title>Echo Panel</title>
	<para>Additionaly terminatorX features a built-in echo
	  effect. It can be configured with this panel.</para>

	<itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Enable
		Button</emphasis></para>

	    <para>Activating this button will enable the echo effect for
	      this turntable.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis>Duration Control</emphasis></para>
	    <para>Use this parameter to set the length of the echo. The
	      duration parameter scales to the actual sample length: so
	      if you set it to 0.5 you will hear the echo when the red
	      playback cursor is half way  through the sample. This is
	      true for samples that are shorter than terminatorX'
	      maximum echo buffer size only.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis>Feedback Control</emphasis></para>
	    <para>Set the echo's feedback amount with this
	      parameter.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis>Volume Control</emphasis></para>
	    <para>This parameter can additionally amplify the echo
	      signal. Unlike the feedback parameter above this parameter
	      has no influence on the signal fed back into the
	      echo-buffer, it effects merely the playback volume of the
	      echo signal.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis>Pan Control</emphasis></para>
	    <para>The echo effect differs from other effects as it's
	      output signal will be mixed seperately. The main goal here
	      is to allow positioning the echo signal at a position in
	      the stereo panorama that differs from the main panning
	      positon of the turntable to achieve a somewhat spacial
	      effect. The easy example is: turntable's panning left,
	      echo's panning right. As both pan parameters are
	      sequencable you can create nice motion effects from this
	      starting point.</para></listitem>


	</itemizedlist></section></section>
    <section id="SYNCHRONIZATION"><title>Synchronization</title>
      <para>Let's start off with an example: Say you have two drumloops
	and one bassline loaded in three turntables. Of course you want
	these samples to be triggered at the same time but you don't
	want to invest time to cut them to the exact length. Therefore
	you decide which of the drumloops to make the sync
	master. You'll have to do this before you enable the audio
	engine (for now). Only one turntable can be the sync master. Now
	you can make the other two sync clients which will cause them to
	be (re-)triggered whenever the master is (re-)triggered. The
	number you can select to the right of the <emphasis>client
	  button</emphasis> sets the trigger delay for the button: if
	it's set to zero the turntable will be triggered with every
	master trigger, if it's set to 1 it'll be triggered every 2nd
	master trigger and so on.</para>

      <para>A nice side effect of this feature is: you can now scratch
	the second (sync client) drum loop and no matter whether you're
	scratching is good or not the beat will be triggered correctly
	again ;)</para></section>

    <section id="GRABMODE"><title>Grab Mode Operation</title>
      <para>After pressing the <emphasis>Mouse Grab button</emphasis>
	terminatorX enters "grab mode". This mode actually locks the
	mouse (as this input is now used to control the realtime
	parameters) and therefore you'll have to know some
	mouse/keyboard shortcuts to control the software without the
	GUI.</para>

      <para>Press <keycap moreinfo="NONE">ESCAPE</keycap> to quit grab mode.</para>
      <para>Select the turntable with input focus: The first turntable
	to hold the input focus will be the first turntable. You can now
	use <keycap moreinfo="NONE">TAB</keycap> or right mouse button
	to switch to the next turntable. Alternativley you can use
	<keycap moreinfo="NONE">F1</keycap> to 
	<keycap moreinfo="NONE">F12</keycap> to select turtntable 1 to 12.</para>

      <para>Now the turntable that has the focus is the one you will
	manipulate with your mouse and keyboard inputs: Note that you
	can actually map different functions to the mouse x/y axis - so
	what actually happens when you move your mouse depends on what
	you select on the x/y control panels for each turntable.</para>

      <table><title>Keyboard Controls in Grab Mode</title>
	<tgroup COLS="2"><thead><row><entry>Key</entry>
	      <entry>Function</entry></row></thead>
	  <tbody><row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">TAB</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>select next turntable</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">F1</keycap> to
		<keycap moreinfo="NONE">F12</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>select turntable 1 to 12</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">RETURN</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>triggers the turntable</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">BACKSPACE</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>stops the turntable</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">S</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>toggles "Sync Client"</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">SPACE</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>while pressed turntable speed is mapped to mouse
		speed (scratching!)</entry></row>

	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">ALT</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>mute on/off</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">CTRL</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>mute on/off (inverted)</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">F</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>("fast") warp mode (while scratching)</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><keycap moreinfo="NONE">W</keycap></entry>
	      <entry>same as above but the audio will be muted while
		warping</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

      <table><title>Mouse Button Controls in Grab Mode</title>
	<tgroup COLS="2"><thead><row><entry>Mouse Button</entry>
	      <entry>Function</entry></row></thead>
	  <tbody><row><entry><emphasis>Left button</emphasis></entry>
	      <entry>same as <keycap moreinfo="NONE">SPACE</keycap>:
		scratching (triggers the turntable when
		stopped)</entry></row>

	    <row><entry><emphasis>Right button</emphasis></entry>
	      <entry>select next turntable</entry></row>
	    <row><entry><emphasis>Middle button</emphasis></entry>
	      <entry>mute on/off</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>
      <para>Scratching works as before: press <keycap
						      moreinfo="NONE">SPACE</keycap> or left mouse button to actually scratch: now your mouse controls the turntables speed. Release it to let that turntable spin at default speed again.</para></section>

    <section id="DRAGNDROP"><title>Drag And Drop</title>
      <para>Since V3.55 terminatorX provides multiple DND-Drop-Targets
	for use with GNOME / gmc (gmc is the GNU Midnight Commander),
	Nautilus or the Elightenment File Manager (efm). You can load an
	audiofile into an existing turntable by dragging it from a gmc
	(or efm or whatever)-window and drop it  over a. the
	<emphasis>file button</emphasis> (audio-display) or b. (the
	easier target ;) over the audio-display (the green on black
	widget that displays the audiodata).</para>

      <para>To add a file to the set (== to load the file into a *new*
	turntable) simply drop the audiofile over the "New Turntable"
	Button. To load a complete terminatorX-set simply drop the
	setfile (*.tX) over the "Load Set" button.</para></section>

    <section id="SEQUENCER"><title>The Sequencer</title>
      <para>Release 3.60 introduced the sequencer. It can record and
	play back events for the following parameters:</para>

      <itemizedlist><listitem><para>master volume &amp; pitch</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>scratching</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>(turntable) volume &amp; pitch</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>triggers</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>loop (on/off)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>sync client settings</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>muting</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><emphasis>all</emphasis> parameters for the
	    effects. This includes built-in effects (lowpass and echo)
	    as well as LADSPA plugins.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>

      <para>To record events simply press the
	<emphasis>Record</emphasis> button of the sequencer, then press
	the <emphasis>Play</emphasis> button. All actions (for
	sequencable parameters - see above) you now take will be
	recorded into the song list. Press <emphasis>Stop</emphasis> and
	<emphasis>Play</emphasis> again to see/hear how terminatorX
	plays back the events recorded before. You can now record events
	again for e.g. another turntable or record other parameters for
	the same turntable - whatever you want to do. Recording events
	for parameters for wich events have been recorded before will
	result in dubbing: if you touch a parameter while recording,
	events previously recorded will be erased from the moment you
	touch the paramater until you stop recording.</para>

      <para>When recording long sequences/songs you can use the
	sequencer-scale to start recording/playback from any
	song-position you want. To record a single paramteter value at a
	certain position simply move the sequencer-scale to that
	position, press <emphasis>Record,</emphasis> set the parameter
	and press <emphasis>Stop</emphasis> again.</para>

      <para>There is no other the way to edit the sequencer events
	currently, but future releases may feature an event-list
	editor.</para></section>

    <section id="LADSPAPLUGINS"><title>Plugins (LADSPA)</title>
      <para>Since release 3.70 terminatorX supports
	LADSPA-plugins. LADSPA is the &quot;Linux Audio Developer's
	Simple Plugin API&quot; which was designed by developers on the
	Linux-Audio-Developer-Mailinglist and is maintained by Richard
	W.E. Furse. For more information on LADSPA, other LADSPA-hosts
	and LADSPA-plugins checkout the 
	<ulink url="http://www.ladspa.org">LADSPA homepage</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Not every plugin is supported by terminatorX though. As the
	plugins are inserted into the per-turntable effect-queue, they
	have to be mono plugins (as is that queue) for now. This is why
	terminatorX will load plugins with <emphasis>one</emphasis>
	audio-in port and <emphasis>one</emphasis> audio-out port
	only.</para>

      <para>The decision on wether a plugin is terminatorX-suitable is
	made on terminatorX startup, so only plugins that fit into the
	effect queue will be offered in the plugin-menu that pops up
	when the <emphasis>FX</emphasis> button is clicked. On startup
	terminatorX will print some information on the LADSPA-plugins
	analysis process to the standard output. Watch the terminal you
	run terminatorX from for that info if you have problems loading
	a plugin.</para>

      <para>As specified in the LADSPA-standard LADSPA-plugins can be
	located in multiple directories across the filesystem. To enable
	LADSPA-hosts to find those plugins you have to set the
	environment variable <ENVAR>LADSPA_PATH</ENVAR>
	accordingly. Let's say you store your plugins in 
	<filename moreinfo="NONE">/usr/lib/ladspa</filename>
	and <filename moreinfo="NONE">/home/yourlogin/plugins</filename>
	then you would have to set:</para>


      <para><ENVAR>LADSPA_PATH</ENVAR>=
	<filename moreinfo="NONE">/usr/lib/ladspa:/home/yourlogin/plugins</filename></para>
      <para>As a fallback terminatorX will look in the standard
	directories <filename moreinfo="NONE">/usr/lib/ladspa</filename>
	and <filename moreinfo="NONE">/usr/local/lib/ladspa</filename>
	if the environment variable  is not set. Note that this is just
	a convenience-function, in order for other LADSPA-hosts to work
	properly, be sure to set your <ENVAR>LADSPA_PATH</ENVAR>
	correctly. It is a good idea to do that from somewhere in your
	system configuration (either in your rc-scripts or 
	<filename moreinfo="NONE">/etc/profile</filename> 
	or whereever you perefer).</para></section></section>

  <section id="CONFIGURATION"><title>Configuration</title>
    <para>All configuration business now happens in the
      Options-dialog. The features that are not completely
      self-explaining do have tooltips.</para>

    <para>A word on the settings in general: your settings are stored in
      the file <filename
			 moreinfo="NONE">~/.terminatorX3rc.bin</filename> so if you think you completely messed up your settings you will have to exit terminatorX - delete this file - and then re-run terminatorX with the default settings.</para>

    <section id="AUDIOSETUP"><title>Audio Setup</title>
      <para>TerminatorX renders audio blockwise. If you want to have
	near-realtime operation you need to have really small
	blocks. The values of these blocks can be influenced via the
	<emphasis>buffer size</emphasis> option. The setting you select
	actually results in a 2^x blocksize (size-setting == 8 -> true
	buffer size in bytes is 2^8=256).</para>

      <para>The problem is the smaller the value you select is the
	faster your machine has to be. So if you here "clicks", or
	"drops" in audio output that are not related to your
	sample-material you will have to increase the buffer size. On
	the other hand if you believe terminatorX does not react fast
	enough you have to decrease this parameter. The default value is
	8, but as my machine handles 7 nicely (running with root
	privileges for realtime scheduling) I use 7.</para></section>

    <section id="MOUSEINPUTSETUP"><title>Mouse/Input Setup</title>
      <para>Between rendering and outputing these blocks terminatorX
	checks for mouse motion. The problem with mice is: they don't
	report when they have stopped. This is why terminatorX assumes
	your mouse has stopped if there is no motion reported for
	certain amount of render/output-cycles. This value is
	configurable via the <emphasis>Stop-sense-cycles</emphasis>
	option. If you decrease your buffsize of course you shorten the
	cycle time as well, therefore if you here strange stop/run
	behaviour of the audio ouput while scratching after you
	decreased the buffersize you might have to increase the
	stop-sense value too.</para>

      <para>Xinput Device: <emphasis>WARNING:</emphasis> Use this option
	*only* if you want to use an input device other than your
	default-mouse for scratching. Selecting your default pointer
	will cause terminatorX to crash. See the "Using a turntable"
	section on the terminatorX homepage for
	details.</para></section>

    <section id="GUISETUP"><title>GUI Setup</title>
      <para>With <emphasis>Update Idle</emphasis> / <emphasis>Update
	  Delay</emphasis> you can configure GUI resposivness: Higher
	<emphasis>Update Idle</emphasis> will cause the wav-display
	(position display) and flash-widgets to update less
	often. Higher <emphasis>Update Delay</emphasis> values will
	cause the parameter widgets to update less
	often.</para></section>

    <section id="SOUNDFILEEDITOR"><title>Soundfile-Editor integration</title>
      <para>You can now enter the soundfile editor of your choice in the
	"Soundfile editor" field. This editor will be started when
	clicking the <emphasis>Edit</emphasis>-button in the  main panel
	of the vtt-gui. If you enter for example "myeditor" terminatorX
	will run "myeditor
	sample_in_vtt.wav".</para></section></section>

  <section id="CONTACT"><title>Contact / Download</title>
    <para>Find out more about terminatorX at it's <ulink url="http://www.terminatorX.cx">homepage</ulink>.</para>
    <para>Send me comments, bug-reports, patches or scratches (see
      scratches section on the terminatorX homepage) at:
      <email>alkoit00@fht-esslingen.de</email></para></section>
</article>



